<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Salue deus rex iudæorum containing, 1. The     passion of Christ, 2. Eues apologie in defence of women, 3. The teares of the daughters of Ierusalem, 4. The salutation and sorrow of the Virgine Marie : with diuers other things not vnfit to be read / written by Mistris Æmilia Lanyer ...</title>
            <title>Salve Deus Rex Judaeorum</title>
            <author>Lanyer, Aemilia.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123202</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38159738</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38159738</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29214</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05085)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29214)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1929:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Salue deus rex iudæorum containing, 1. The     passion of Christ, 2. Eues apologie in defence of women, 3. The teares of the daughters of Ierusalem, 4. The salutation and sorrow of the Virgine Marie : with diuers other things not vnfit to be read / written by Mistris Æmilia Lanyer ...</title>
                  <title>Salve Deus Rex Judaeorum</title>
                  <author>Lanyer, Aemilia.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[110] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Valentine Simmes for Richard Bonian, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint in four lines.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁴(-a1) b-e⁴, f³, A-H⁴ I² (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian poetry, English.</term>
               <term>Women --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:1"/>
            <p>SALVE DEVS REX IVDAEORVM.</p>
            <p>Containing,
<list>
                  <item>1 The Paſsion of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2 Eues Apologie in defence of Women.</item>
                  <item>3 The Teares of the Daughters of Ieruſalem.</item>
                  <item>4 The Salutation and Sorrow of the Virgine Marie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With diuers other things not vnfit to be read.</p>
            <p>Written by Miſtris <hi>Aemilia Lanyer,</hi> Wife to Captaine <hi>Alfonſo Lanyer</hi> Seruant to the Kings Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine Simmes</hi> for <hi>Richard Bonian,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. <hi>Anno</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Queenes moſt Excellent Majeſtie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REnowned Empreſſe, and great Britaines Queene,</l>
               <l>Moſt gratious Mother of ſucceeding Kings;</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe to view that which is ſeldome ſeene,</l>
               <l>A Womans writing of diuinest things:</l>
               <l>Reade it faire Queene, though it defectiue be,</l>
               <l>Your Excellence can grace both It and Mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For you haue rifled Nature of her ſtore,</l>
               <l>And all the Goddeſſes haue diſpoſſeſt</l>
               <l>Of thoſe rich gifts which they enioy'd before,</l>
               <l>But now great Queene, in you they all doe reſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>If now they ſtriued for the golden Ball,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paris</hi> would gine it you before them all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From <hi>Iuno</hi> you haue State and Dignities,</l>
               <l>From warlike <hi>Pallas,</hi> Wiſdome, Fortitude;</l>
               <l>And from faire <hi>Venus</hi> all her Excellencies,</l>
               <l>With their beſt parts your Highneſſe is indu'd:</l>
               <l>How much are we to honor thoſe that ſprings</l>
               <l>From ſuch rare beauty, in the blood of Kings?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Muſes doe attend vpon your Throne,</l>
               <l>With all the Artiſts at your becke and call;</l>
               <l>The Syluane Gods, and Satyres euery one,</l>
               <l>Before your faire triumphant Chariot fall:</l>
               <l>And ſhining Cynthia with her nymphs attend</l>
               <l>To honour you, whoſe Honour hath no end.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>From your bright ſpheare of greatnes where you ſit,</l>
               <l>Reflecting light to all thoſe glorious ſtars</l>
               <l>That wait vpon your Throane; To virtue yet</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe that ſplendor which my meanneſſe bars:</l>
               <l>Be like faire <hi>Phoebe,</hi> who doth loue to grace</l>
               <l>The darkeſt night with her moſt beauteous face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo's</hi> beames doe comfort euery creature,</l>
               <l>And ſhines vpon the meaneſt things that be;</l>
               <l>Since in Eſtate and Virtue none is greater,</l>
               <l>I humbly wiſh that yours may light on me:</l>
               <l>That ſo theſe rude vnpolliſht lines of mine,</l>
               <l>Graced by you, may ſeeme the more diuine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke in this Mirrour of a worthy Mind,</l>
               <l>Where ſome of your faire Virtues will appeare;</l>
               <l>Though all it is impoſſible to find,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe my Glaſſe were chryſtall, or more cleare:</l>
               <l>Which is dym ſteele, yet full of ſpotleſſe truth,</l>
               <l>And for one looke from your faire eyes it ſu'th.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here may your ſacred Maieſtie behold</l>
               <l>That mightie Monarch both of heau'n and earth,</l>
               <l>He that all Nations of the world controld,</l>
               <l>Yet tooke our fleſh in baſe and meaneſt berth:</l>
               <l>Whoſe daies were ſpent in pouerty and ſorrow,</l>
               <l>And yet all Kings their wealth of him do borrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he is Crowne and Crowner of all Kings,</l>
               <l>The hopefull hauen of the meaner ſort,</l>
               <l>Its he that all our ioyfull tidings brings</l>
               <l>Of happie raigne within his royall Court:</l>
               <l>Its he that in extremity can giue</l>
               <l>Comfort to them that haue no time to liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſince my wealth within his Region ſtands,</l>
               <l>And that his Croſſe my chiefeſt comfort is,</l>
               <l>Yea in his kingdome onely reſts my lands,</l>
               <l>Of honour there I hope I ſhall not miſſe:</l>
               <l>Though I on earth doe liue vnfortunate,</l>
               <l>Yet there I may attaine a better ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In the meane time, accept moſt gratious Queene</l>
               <l>This holy worke, Virtne preſents to you,</l>
               <l>In poore apparell, ſhaming to be ſeene,</l>
               <l>Or once t'appeare in your iudiciall view:</l>
               <l>But that faire Virtue, though in meane attire,</l>
               <l>All Princes of the world doe moſt deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſith all royall virtues are in you,</l>
               <l>The Naturall, the Morall, and Diuine,</l>
               <l>I hope how plaine ſoeuer, beeing true,</l>
               <l>You will accept euen of the meaneſt line</l>
               <l>Faire Virtue yeelds; by whoſe rare gifts you are</l>
               <l>So highly grac'd, t'exceed the faireſt faire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Behold, great Queene, faire <hi>Eues</hi> Apologie,</l>
               <l>Which I haue writ in honour of your ſexe,</l>
               <l>And doe referre vnto your Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>To iudge if it agree not with the Text:</l>
               <l>And if it doe, why are poore Women blam'd,</l>
               <l>Or by more faultie Men ſo much defam'd?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And this great Lady I haue here attired,</l>
               <l>In all her richeſt ornaments of Honour,</l>
               <l>That you faire Queene, of all the world admired,</l>
               <l>May take the more delight to looke vpon her:</l>
               <l>For ſhe muſt entertaine you to this Feaſt,</l>
               <l>To which your Highneſſe is the welcom'ſt gueſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>For here I haue prepar'd my Paſchal Lambe,</l>
               <l>The figure of that liuing Sacrifice;</l>
               <l>Who dying, all th' Infernall powres orecame,</l>
               <l>That we with him t'Eternitie might riſe:</l>
               <l>This pretious Paſſeouer feed vpon, O Queene,</l>
               <l>Let your faire Virtues in my Glaſſe be ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſhe that is the patterne of all Beautie,</l>
               <l>The very modell of your Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Whoſe rareſt parts enforceth Loue and Duty,</l>
               <l>The perfect patterne of all Pietie:</l>
               <l>O let my Booke by her faire eies be bleſt,</l>
               <l>In whoſe pure thoughts all Innocency reſts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſhall I thinke my Glaſſe a glorious Skie,</l>
               <l>When two ſuch glittring Suns at once appeare;</l>
               <l>The one repleat with Sou'raigne Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Both ſhining brighter than the cleareſt cleare:</l>
               <l>And both reflecting comfort to my ſpirits,</l>
               <l>To find their grace ſo much aboue my merits</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe vntun'd voyce the dolefull notes doth ſing</l>
               <l>Of ſad Affliction in an humble ſtraine;</l>
               <l>Much like vnto a Bird that wants a wing,</l>
               <l>And cannot flie, but warbles forth her paine:</l>
               <l>Or he that barred from the Suns bright light,</l>
               <l>Wanting daies comfort, doth comend the night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So I that liue cloſ'd vp in Sorrowes Cell,</l>
               <l>Since great <hi>Elizaes</hi> fauour bleſt my youth;</l>
               <l>And in the confines of all cares doe dwell,</l>
               <l>Whoſe grieued eyes no pleaſure euer view'th:</l>
               <l>But in Chriſts ſuffrings, ſuch ſweet taſte they haue,</l>
               <l>As makes me praiſe pale Sorrow and the Graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And this great Ladie whom I loue and honour,</l>
               <l>And from my very tender yeeres haue knowne,</l>
               <l>This holy habite ſtill to take vpon her,</l>
               <l>Still to remaine <hi>the ſame,</hi> and ſtill her owne:</l>
               <l>And what our fortunes doe enforce vs to,</l>
               <l>She of Deuotion and meere Zeale doth do.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which makes me thinke our heauy burden light,</l>
               <l>When ſuch a one as ſhe will help to beare it:</l>
               <l>Treading the paths that make our way go right,</l>
               <l>What garment is ſo faire but ſhe may weare it;</l>
               <l>Eſpecially for her that entertaines</l>
               <l>A Glorious Queene, in whome all woorth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe powre may raiſe my ſad deiected Muſe,</l>
               <l>From this lowe Manſion of a troubled mind;</l>
               <l>Whoſe princely fauour may ſuch grace infuſe,</l>
               <l>That I may ſpread Her Virtues in like kind:</l>
               <l>But in this triall of my ſlender skill,</l>
               <l>I wanted knowledge to performe my will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For euen as they that doe behold the Starres,</l>
               <l>Not with the eie of Learning, but of Sight,</l>
               <l>To find their motions, want of knowledge barres</l>
               <l>Although they ſee them in their brighteſt light:</l>
               <l>So, though I ſee the glory of her State,</l>
               <l>Its ſhe that must instruct and eleuate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My weake distempred braine and feeble ſpirits,</l>
               <l>Which all vnlearned haue aduentur'd, this</l>
               <l>To write of Christ, and of his ſacred merits,</l>
               <l>Deſiring that this Booke Her hands may kiſſe:</l>
               <l>And though I be vnworthy of that grace,</l>
               <l>Yet let her bleſſed thoghts this book imbrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And pardon me (faire Queene) though I preſume,</l>
               <l>To doe that which ſo many better can;</l>
               <l>Not that I Learning to my ſelfe aſſume,</l>
               <l>Or that I would compare with any man:</l>
               <l>But as they are Scholers, and by Art do write,</l>
               <l>So Nature yeelds my Soule a ſad delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſince all Arts at first from Nature came,</l>
               <l>That goodly Creature, Mother of Perfection,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Ioues</hi> almighty hand at first did frame,</l>
               <l>Taking both her and hers in his protection:</l>
               <l>Why ſhould not She now grace my barren Muſe,</l>
               <l>And in a Woman all defects excuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So peereleſſe Princeſſe humbly I deſire,</l>
               <l>That your great wiſedome would vouchſafe t'omit</l>
               <l>All faults; and pardon if my ſpirits retire,</l>
               <l>Leauing to ayme at what they cannot hit:</l>
               <l>To write your worth, which no pen can expreſſe,</l>
               <l>Were but t'ecclipſe your Fame, and make it leſſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:5"/>
            <head>To the Lady <hi>ELIZABETHS</hi> Grace.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MOſt gratious Ladie, faire ELIZABETH,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Name and Virtues puts vs ſtill in mind,</l>
               <l>Of her, of whom we are depriu'd by death;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> of her age, whoſe worth did bind</l>
               <l>All worthy minds ſo long as they haue breath,</l>
               <l>In linkes of Admiration, loue and zeale,</l>
               <l>To that deare Mother of our Common-weale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Euen you faire Princeſſe next our famous Queene,</l>
               <l>I doe inuite vnto this wholeſome feaſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe goodly wiſedome, though your yeares be greene,</l>
               <l>By ſuch good workes may daily be increaſt,</l>
               <l>Though your faire eyes farre better Bookes haue ſeene;</l>
               <l>Yet being the firſt fruits of a womans wit,</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe you fauour in accepting it.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_ladies">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:6"/>
            <head>To all vertuous Ladies in generall.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>EAch bleſſed Lady that in Virtue ſpends</l>
               <l>Your pretious time to beautifie your ſoules;</l>
               <l>Come wait on hir whom winged Fame attends</l>
               <l>And in hir hand the Booke where ſhe inroules</l>
               <l>Thoſe high deſerts that Maiestie commends:</l>
               <l>Let this faire Queene not vnattended bee,</l>
               <l>When in my Glaſſe ſhe daines her ſelfe to ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Put on your wedding garments euery one,</l>
               <l>The Bridegroome ſtayes to entertaine you all;</l>
               <l>Let Virtue be your guide, for ſhe alone</l>
               <l>Can leade you right that you can neuer fall;</l>
               <l>And make no ſtay for feare he ſhould be gone:</l>
               <l>But fill your Lamps with oyle of burning zeale,</l>
               <l>That to your Faith he may his Truth reueale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let all your roabes be purple ſcarlet white,
<note place="margin">The roabes that Chriſt wore before his death.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe perfit colours purest Virtue wore,</l>
               <l>Come deckt with Lillies that did ſo delight</l>
               <l>To be preferr'd in Beauty, farre before</l>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his glory dight:</l>
               <l>Whoſe royall roabes did no ſuch pleaſure yield,</l>
               <l>As did the beauteous Lilly of the field.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Adorne your temples with faire <hi>Daphnes</hi> crowne,</l>
               <l>The neuer changing Laurel, alwaies geene;</l>
               <l>Let conſtant hope all worldly pleaſures drowne,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n token of Conſtancie.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In wiſe <hi>Mineruaes</hi> paths be alwaies ſcene;</l>
               <l>Or with bright <hi>Cynthia,</hi> thogh faire <hi>Venus</hi> frown:</l>
               <l>With <hi>Eſop</hi> croſſe the poſts of euery doore,</l>
               <l>Where Sinne would riot, making Virtue poore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And let the Muſes your companions be,</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſacred ſiſters that on <hi>Pallas</hi> wait;</l>
               <l>Whoſe Virtues with the pureſt minds agree,</l>
               <l>Whoſe godly labours doe auoyd the baite</l>
               <l>Of worldly pleaſures, liuing alwaies free</l>
               <l>From ſword, from violence, and from ill report,</l>
               <l>To theſe nine Worthies all faire mindes reſort.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Annoynt your haire with <hi>Aarons</hi> pretious oyle,</l>
               <l>And bring your palmes of vict'ry in your hands,</l>
               <l>To ouercome all thoughts that would defile</l>
               <l>The earthly circuit of your ſoules faire lands;</l>
               <l>Let no dimme ſhadowes your cleare eyes beguile:</l>
               <l>Sweet odours, mirrhe, gum, aloes, frankincenſe,</l>
               <l>Preſent that King who di'd for your offence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Behold, bright <hi>Titans</hi> ſhining chariot ſtaies,</l>
               <l>All deckt with flowers of the freſheſt hew,</l>
               <l>Attended on by Age, Houres, Nights, and Daies,</l>
               <l>Which alters not your beauty, but giues you</l>
               <l>Much more, and crownes you with eternall praiſe:</l>
               <l>This golden chariot wherein you muſt ride,</l>
               <l>Let ſimple Doues, and ſubtill ſerpents guide.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Come ſwifter than the motion of the Sunne,</l>
               <l>To be transfigur'd with our louing Lord,</l>
               <l>Leſt Glory end what Grace in you begun,</l>
               <l>Of heau'nly riches make your greateſt hoord,</l>
               <l>In Chriſt all honour, wealth, and beautie's wonne:</l>
               <l>By whoſe perfections you appeare more faire</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Phoebus,</hi> if he ſeau'n times brighter were.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gods holy Angels will direct your Doues,</l>
               <l>And bring your Serpents to the fields of reſt,</l>
               <l>Where he doth ſtay that purchaſt all your loues</l>
               <l>In bloody torments, when he di'd oppreſt,</l>
               <l>There ſhall you find him in thoſe pleaſant groues</l>
               <l>Of ſweet <hi>Elizium,</hi> by the Well of Life,</l>
               <l>Whoſe criſtal ſprings do purge from worldly ſtrife</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus may you flie from dull and ſenſuall earth,</l>
               <l>Whereof at firſt your bodies formed were,</l>
               <l>That new regen'rate in a ſecond berth,</l>
               <l>Your bleſſed ſoules may liue without all feare,</l>
               <l>Beeing immortall, ſubiect to no death:</l>
               <l>But in the eie of heauen ſo highly placed,</l>
               <l>That others by your virtues may be graced.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where worthy Ladies I will leaue you all,</l>
               <l>Deſiring you to grace this little Booke;</l>
               <l>Yet ſome of you me thinkes I heare to call</l>
               <l>Me by my name, and bid me better looke,</l>
               <l>Leſt vnawares I in an error fall:</l>
               <l>In generall tearmes, to place you with the reſt,</l>
               <l>Whom Fame commends to be the very beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Tis true, I must confeſſe (O noble Fame)</l>
               <l>There are a number honoured by thee,</l>
               <l>Of which, ſome few thou didst recite by name,</l>
               <l>And willd my Muſe they ſhould remembred bee;</l>
               <l>Wiſhing ſome would their glorious Trophies frame:</l>
               <l>Which if I ſhould preſume to vndertake,</l>
               <l>My tired Hand for very feare would quake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Onely by name I will bid ſome of thoſe,</l>
               <l>That in true Honors ſeate haue long bin placed,</l>
               <l>Yea euen ſuch as thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chiefly choſe,</l>
               <l>By whom my Muſe may be the better graced;</l>
               <l>Therefore, vnwilling longer time to loſe,</l>
               <l>I will inuite ſome Ladies that I know,</l>
               <l>But chiefly thoſe as thou hast graced ſo.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:8"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Ladie <hi>Arabella.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>GReat learned Ladie, whom I long haue knowne,</l>
               <l>And yet not knowne ſo much as I deſired:</l>
               <l>Rare <hi>Phoenix,</hi> whoſe faire feathers are your owne,</l>
               <l>With which you flie, and are ſo much admired:</l>
               <l>True honour whom true Fame hath ſo attired,</l>
               <l>In glittering raiment ſhining much more bright,</l>
               <l>Than ſiluer Starres in the moſt froſtie night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come like the morning Sunne new out of bed,</l>
               <l>And caſt your eyes vpon this little Booke,</l>
               <l>Although you be ſo well accompan'ed</l>
               <l>With <hi>Pallas,</hi> and the Muſes, ſpare one looke</l>
               <l>Vpon this humbled King, who all forſooke,</l>
               <l>That in his dying armes he might imbrace</l>
               <l>Your beauteous Soule, and fill it with his grace.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:9"/>
            <head>¶ To the Ladie <hi>Suſan,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe Dowager of Kent, and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Ducheſſe of Suffolke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>COme you that were the Mistris of my youth,</l>
               <l>The noble guide of my vngouern'd dayes;</l>
               <l>Come you that haue delighted in Gods truth,</l>
               <l>Help now your handmaid to ſound foorth his praiſe:</l>
               <l>You that are pleas'd in his pure excellencie,</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe to grace this holy feast, and me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as your rare Perfections ſhew'd the Glaſſe</l>
               <l>Wherein I ſaw each wrinckle of a fault;</l>
               <l>You the Sunnes virtue, I that faire greene graſſe,</l>
               <l>That flouriſht freſh by your cleere virtues taught:</l>
               <l>For you poſſest thoſe gifts that grace the mind,</l>
               <l>Restraining youth whom Errour oft doth blind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In you theſe noble Virtues did I note,</l>
               <l>First, loue and feare of God, of Prince, of Lawes,</l>
               <l>Rare Patience with a mind ſo farre remote</l>
               <l>From worldly pleaſures, free from giuing cauſe</l>
               <l>Of least ſuspect to the most enuious eie,</l>
               <l>That in faire Virtues Storehouſe ſought to prie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe Faith did vndertake in Infancie,</l>
               <l>All dang'rous trauells by deuouring Seas</l>
               <l>To flie to Christ from vaine Idolatry,</l>
               <l>Not ſeeking there this worthleſſe world to pleaſe,</l>
               <l>By your most famous Mother ſo directed,</l>
               <l>That noble Dutcheſſe, who liu'd vnſubiected.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>From <hi>Romes</hi> ridiculous prier and tyranny,</l>
               <l>That mighty Monarchs kept in awfull feare;</l>
               <l>Leauing here her lands, her ſtate, dignitie;</l>
               <l>Nay more, vouchſaft diſgniſed weedes to weare:</l>
               <l>When with Chriſt Ieſus ſhe did meane to goe,</l>
               <l>From ſweet delights to taste part of his woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come you that euer ſince hath followed her,</l>
               <l>In theſe ſweet paths of faire Humilitie;</l>
               <l>Contemning Pride pure <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtue to preferre,</l>
               <l>Not yeelding to baſe Imbecillitie,</l>
               <l>Nor to thoſe weake inticements of the world,</l>
               <l>That haue ſo many thouſand Soules inſnarld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Receiue your Loue whom you haue ſought ſo farre,</l>
               <l>Which heere preſents himſelfe within your view;</l>
               <l>Behold this bright and all directing Starre,</l>
               <l>Light of your Soule that doth all grace renew:</l>
               <l>And in his humble paths ſince you do tread,</l>
               <l>Take this faire Bridegroome in your ſoules pure bed,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſince no former gaine hath made me write,</l>
               <l>Nor my deſertleſſe ſeruice could haue wonne,</l>
               <l>Onely your noble Virtues do incite</l>
               <l>My Pen, they are the ground I write vpon;</l>
               <l>Nor any future profit is expected,</l>
               <l>Then how can theſe poore lines goe vnrespected?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:10"/>
            <head>¶ The Authors Dreame to the Ladie <hi>Marie,</hi> the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe <hi>Dowager of Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ME thought I paſs'd through th' <hi>Edalyan</hi> Groues,</l>
               <l>And askt the Graces, if they could direct,</l>
               <l>Me to a Lady whom <hi>Minerua</hi> choſe,</l>
               <l>To liue with her in height of all reſpect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet looking backe into my thoughts againe,</l>
               <l>The eie of Reaſon did behold her there</l>
               <l>Faſt ti'd vnto them in a golden Chaine,</l>
               <l>They ſtood, but ſhe was ſet in Honors chaire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And nine faire Virgins ſate vpon the ground,</l>
               <l>With Harps and Vialls in their lilly hands;</l>
               <l>Whoſe harmony had all my ſences drown'd,</l>
               <l>But that before mine eyes an object ſtands,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe Beauty ſhin'd like <hi>Titons</hi> cleereſt raies,</l>
               <l>She blew a braſen Trumpet, which did ſound</l>
               <l>Throgh al the world that worthy Ladies praiſe,</l>
               <l>And by Eternall Fame I ſaw her crown'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſtudying, if I were awake, or no,</l>
               <l>God <hi>Morphy</hi> came and tooke me by the hand,
<note place="margin">The God of Dreames.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And wil'd me not from Slumbers bowre to go,</l>
               <l>Till I the ſumme of all did vnderſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>When preſently the Welkin that before</l>
               <l>Look'd bright and cleere, me thought, was ouercaſt,</l>
               <l>And duskie clouds, with boyſt'rous winds great ſtore,</l>
               <l>Foretold of violent ſtormes which could not laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And gazing vp into the troubled skie,</l>
               <l>Me thought a Chariot did from thence deſcend,</l>
               <l>Where one did ſit repleat with Majeſtie,</l>
               <l>Drawne by foure fierie Dragons, which did bend</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their courſe where this moſt noble Lady ſate,</l>
               <l>Whom all theſe virgins with due reuerence</l>
               <l>Did entertaine, according to that ſtate</l>
               <l>Which did belong vnto her Excellence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When bright <hi>Bellona,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Goddeſſe of Warre and Wiſdome.</note> ſo they did her call,</l>
               <l>Whom theſe faire Nymphs ſo humbly did receiue,</l>
               <l>Amanly mayd which was both faire and tall,</l>
               <l>Her borrowed Charret by a ſpring did leaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With ſpeare, and ſhield, and currat on her breaſt,</l>
               <l>And on her head a helmet wondrous bright,</l>
               <l>With myrtle, bayes, and oliue branches dreſt,</l>
               <l>Wherein me thought I tooke no ſmall delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſee how all the Graces ſought grace here,</l>
               <l>And in what meeke, yet princely ſort ſhee came;</l>
               <l>How this moſt noble Lady did imbrace her,</l>
               <l>And all humors vnto hers did frame.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Now faire <hi>Dictina</hi> by the breake of Day,
<note place="margin">The Moone.</note>
               </l>
               <l>With all her Damſels round about her came,</l>
               <l>Ranging the woods to hunt, yet made a ſtay,</l>
               <l>When harkning to the pleaſing ſound of Fame;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her Iuory bowe and ſiluer ſhaftes ſhee gaue</l>
               <l>Vnto the faireſt nymphe of all her traine;</l>
               <l>And wondring who it was that in ſo graue,</l>
               <l>Yet gallant faſhion did her beauty ſtaine:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee deckt her ſelfe with all the borrowed light</l>
               <l>That <hi>Phoebus</hi> would afford from his faire face,</l>
               <l>And made her Virgins to appeare ſo bright,</l>
               <l>That all the hils and vales receiued grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then preſſing where this beauteous troupe did ſtand,</l>
               <l>They all receiued her moſt willingly,</l>
               <l>And vnto her the Lady gaue her hand,</l>
               <l>That ſhee ſhould keepe with them continually.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurora</hi> riſing from her roſie bedde,
<note place="margin">The Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Firſt bluſht, then wept, to ſee faire <hi>Phoebe</hi> grac'd,</l>
               <l>And vnto Lady <hi>Maie</hi> theſe wordes ſhee ſed,</l>
               <l>Come, let vs goe, we will not be out-fac'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I will vnto <hi>Apolloes</hi> Waggoner,</l>
               <l>A bidde him bring his Maſter preſently,</l>
               <l>That his bright beames may all her Beauty marre,</l>
               <l>Gracing vs with the luſter of his eie.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Come, come, ſweet Maie, and fill their laps with floures,</l>
               <l>And I will giue a greater light than ſhe:</l>
               <l>So all theſe Ladied fauours ſhall be ours,</l>
               <l>None ſhall be more eſteem'd than we ſhall be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus did <hi>Aurora</hi> dimme faire <hi>Phoebus</hi> light,</l>
               <l>And was receiu'd in bright <hi>Cynthiaes</hi> place,</l>
               <l>While <hi>Flora</hi> all with fragrant floures dight,</l>
               <l>Preſſed to ſhew the beauty of her face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though theſe, me thought, were verie pleaſing ſights,</l>
               <l>Yet now theſe Worthies did agree to go,</l>
               <l>Vnto a place full of all rare delights,</l>
               <l>A place that yet <hi>Minerua</hi> did not know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ſacred Spring where Artand Nature ſtriu'd</l>
               <l>Which ſhould remaine as Sou'raigne of the place;</l>
               <l>Whoſe antient quarrell being new reuiu'd,</l>
               <l>Added freſh Beauty, gaue farre greater Grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To which as vmpiers now theſe Ladies go,</l>
               <l>Iudging with pleaſure their delightfull caſe;</l>
               <l>Whoſe rauiſht ſences made them quickely know,</l>
               <l>T'would be offenſiue either to diſplace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therefore will'd they ſhould for euer dwell,</l>
               <l>In perfit vnity by this matchleſſe Spring:</l>
               <l>Since 'twas impoſſible either ſhould excell,</l>
               <l>Or her faire fellow in ſubjection bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But here in equall ſou'raigntie to liue,</l>
               <l>Equall in ſtate, equall in dignitie,</l>
               <l>That vnto others they might comfort giue,</l>
               <l>Rejoycing all with their ſweet vnitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now me thought I long to heare her name,</l>
               <l>Whom wiſe <hi>Minerua</hi> honoured ſo much,</l>
               <l>Shee whom I ſaw was crownd by noble Fame,</l>
               <l>Whom Enuy ſought to ſting, yet could not tuch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Me thought the meager elfe did ſecke bie waies</l>
               <l>To come vnto her, but it would not be;</l>
               <l>Her venime purifi'd by virtues raies,</l>
               <l>Shee pin'd and ſtaru'd like an Anotomie:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While beauteous <hi>Pallas</hi> with this Lady faire,</l>
               <l>Attended by theſe Nymphs of noble fame,</l>
               <l>Beheld thoſe woods, thoſe groues, thoſe bowers rare,</l>
               <l>By which <hi>Perguſa,</hi> for ſo hight the name</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of that faire ſpring, his dwelling place &amp; ground;</l>
               <l>And throgh thoſe fields with ſundry flowers clad,</l>
               <l>Ofſeu'rall colours, to adorne the ground,</l>
               <l>And pleaſe the ſences eu'n of the moſt ſad:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He trayld along the woods in wanton wiſe,</l>
               <l>With ſweet delight to entertaine them all;</l>
               <l>Inuiting them to ſit and to deuiſe</l>
               <l>On holy hymnes; at laſt to mind they call</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:13"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe rare ſweet ſongs which <hi>Iſraels</hi> King did frame</l>
               <l>Vnto the Father of Eternitie;
<note place="margin">The Pſalms written new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Counteſſe Dowager of Penbrooke.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Before his holy wiſedom tooke the name</l>
               <l>Of great <hi>Meſſias,</hi> Lord of vnitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe holy Sonnets they did all agree,</l>
               <l>With this moſt louely Lady here to ſing;</l>
               <l>That by her noble breaſts ſweet harmony,</l>
               <l>Their muſicke might in eares of Angels ring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While ſaints like Swans about this ſiluer brook</l>
               <l>Should <hi>Hallalu-iah</hi> ſing continually,</l>
               <l>Writing her praiſes in th'eternall booke.</l>
               <l>Of endleſſe honour, true fames memorie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus I in ſleep the heauenli'ſt muſicke hard,</l>
               <l>That euer earthly eares did entertaine;</l>
               <l>And durſt not wake, for feare to be debard</l>
               <l>Of what my ſences ſought ſtill to retaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſleeping, praid dull Slumber to vnfold</l>
               <l>Her noble name, who was of all admired;</l>
               <l>When preſently in drowſie tearmes he told</l>
               <l>Not onely that, but more than I deſired.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This nymph, quoth he, great <hi>Penbrooke</hi> hight by name,</l>
               <l>Siſter to valiant <hi>Sidney,</hi> whoſe cleere light</l>
               <l>Giues light to all that tread true paths of Fame,</l>
               <l>Who in the globe of heau'n doth ſhine ſo bright;</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:13"/>
            <lg>
               <l>That beeing dead, his fame doth him ſuruiue,</l>
               <l>Still liuing in the hearts of worthy men;</l>
               <l>Pale Death is dead, but he remaines aliue,</l>
               <l>Whoſe dying wounds reſtor'd him life agen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And this faire earthly goddeſſe which you ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bellona</hi> and her virgins doe attend;</l>
               <l>In virtuous ſtudies of Diuinitie,</l>
               <l>Her pretious time continually doth ſpend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So that a Siſter well ſhee may be deemd,</l>
               <l>To him that liu'd and di'd ſo nobly;</l>
               <l>And farre before him is to be eſteemd</l>
               <l>For virtue, wiſedome, learning, dignity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe beauteous ſoule hath gain'd a double life,</l>
               <l>Both here on earth, and in the heau'ns aboue,</l>
               <l>Till diſſolution end all worldly ſtrife:</l>
               <l>Her bleſſed ſpirit remaines, of holy loue,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Directing all by her immortall light,</l>
               <l>In this huge ſea of ſorrowes, griefes, and feares;</l>
               <l>With contemplation of Gods powrefull might,</l>
               <l>Shee ſils the eies, the hearts, the tongues, the eares</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of after-comming ages, which ſhall reade</l>
               <l>Her loue, her zeale, her faith, and pietie;</l>
               <l>The faire impreſſion of whoſe worthy deed,</l>
               <l>Seales her pure ſoule vnto the Deitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:14"/>
            <lg>
               <l>That both in Hean'n and Earth it may remaine,</l>
               <l>Crownd with her Makers glory and his loue;</l>
               <l>And this did Father Slumber tell with paine,</l>
               <l>Whoſe dulneſſe ſcarce could ſuffer him to moue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When I awaking left him and his bowre,</l>
               <l>Much grieued that I could no longer ſtay;</l>
               <l>Senceleſſe was ſleepe, not to admit me powre,</l>
               <l>As I had ſpent the night to ſpend the day:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then had God <hi>Morphie</hi> ſhew'd the end of all,</l>
               <l>And what my heart deſir'd, mine eies had ſeene;</l>
               <l>For as I wak'd me thought I heard one call</l>
               <l>For that bright Charet lent by <hi>Ioues</hi> faire Queene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou, baſe cunning thiefe, that robs our ſprits</l>
               <l>Of halfe that ſpan of life which yeares doth giue;
<note place="margin">To Sleepe.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And yet no praiſe vnto thy ſelfe it merits,</l>
               <l>To make a ſeeming death in thoſe that liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea wickedly thou doeſt conſent to death,</l>
               <l>Within thy reſtfull bed to rob our ſoules;</l>
               <l>In Slumbers bowre thou ſteal'ſt away our breath,</l>
               <l>Yet none there is that thy baſe ſtealths controules.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If poore and ſickly creatures would imbrace thee,</l>
               <l>Or they to whom thou giu'ſt a taſte of pleaſure,</l>
               <l>Thou fli'ſt as if <hi>Acteons</hi> hounds did chaſe thee,</l>
               <l>Or that to ſtay with them thou hadſt no leaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:14"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But though thou haſt depriu'd me of delight,</l>
               <l>By ſtealing from me ere I was aware;</l>
               <l>I know I ſhall enioy the ſelfe ſame ſight,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt no powre my waking ſprites to barre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For to this Lady now I will repaire,</l>
               <l>Preſenting her the fruits of idle houres;</l>
               <l>Thogh many Books ſhe writes that are more rare,</l>
               <l>Yet there is hony in the meaneſt flowres:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which is both wholeſome, and delights the taſte:</l>
               <l>Though ſugar be more finer, higher priz'd,</l>
               <l>Yet is the painefull Bee no whit diſgrac'd,</l>
               <l>Nor her faire wax, or hony more deſpiz'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though that learned damſell and the reſt,</l>
               <l>Haue in a higher ſtyle her Trophie fram'd;</l>
               <l>Yet theſe vnlearned lines beeing my beſt,</l>
               <l>Of her great wiſedom can no whit be blam'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therefore, firſt I here preſent my Dreame,</l>
               <l>And next, inuite her Honour to my feaſt;</l>
               <l>For my cleare reaſon ſees her by that ſtreame,</l>
               <l>Where her rare virtues daily are increaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So crauing pardon for this bold attempt,</l>
               <l>I here preſent my mirrour to her view,</l>
               <l>Whoſe noble virtues cannot be exempt,</l>
               <l>My Glaſſe beeing ſteele, declares them to be true.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And Madame, if you will vouchſafe that grace,</l>
               <l>To grace thoſe flowres that ſprings from virtues ground;</l>
               <l>Though your faire mind on worthier workes is plac'd,</l>
               <l>On workes that are more deepe, and more profound;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet is it no diſparagement to you,</l>
               <l>To ſee your Sauiour in a Shepheards weed,</l>
               <l>Vnworthily preſented in your viewe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe worthineſſe will grace each line you reade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Receiue him here by my vnworthy hand,</l>
               <l>And reade his paths of faire humility;</l>
               <l>Who though our ſinnes in number paſſe the ſand,</l>
               <l>They all are purg'd by his Diuinity.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:15"/>
            <head>¶ To the Ladie <hi>Lucie,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Bedford.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ME thinkes I ſee faire Virtue readie ſtand,</l>
               <l>T'vnlocke the cloſet of your louely breast,</l>
               <l>Holding the key of Knowledge in her hand,</l>
               <l>Key of that Cabbine where your ſelfe doth rest,</l>
               <l>To let him in, by whom her youth was bleſt:</l>
               <l>The true-loue of your ſoule, your hearts delight,</l>
               <l>Fairer than all the world in your cleare ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that deſcended from celeſtiall glory,</l>
               <l>To taſte of our infirmities and ſorrowes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe heauenly wiſdom read the earthly ſtorie</l>
               <l>Offraile Humanity, which his godhead borrows?</l>
               <l>Loe here he coms all ſtucke with pale deaths arrows:</l>
               <l>In whoſe most pretious wounds your ſoule may reade</l>
               <l>Saluation, while he (dying Lord) doth bleed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You whoſe cleare Iudgement farre exceeds my skil,</l>
               <l>Vonchſafe to entertaine this dying louer,</l>
               <l>The Ocean of true grace, whoſe ſtreames doe fill</l>
               <l>All thoſe with Ioy, that can his loue recouer;</l>
               <l>About this bleſſed Arke bright Angels houer:</l>
               <l>Where your faire ſoule may ſure and ſafely reſt,</l>
               <l>When he is ſweetly ſeated in your breſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:16"/>
            <lg>
               <l>There may your thoughts as ſeruants to your heart,</l>
               <l>Giue true attendance on this louely guest,</l>
               <l>While he doth to that bleſſed bowre impart</l>
               <l>Flowres of freſh comforts, decke that bed of rest,</l>
               <l>With ſuch rich beauties as may make it bleſt:</l>
               <l>And you in whom all raritie is found,</l>
               <l>May be with his eternall glory crownd.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:16"/>
            <head>To the Ladie <hi>Margaret</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe Dowager of Cumberland.</head>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honoutable and Excellent Lady, I may ſay with Saint <hi>Peter, Siluer nor gold haue I none, but ſuch as I haue, that giue I you:</hi> for hauing neither rich pearles of India, nor fine gold of Arabia, nor diamonds of ineſtimable value; neither thoſe rich treaſures, Arramaticall Gums, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, and ſweet odours, which were preſented by thoſe Kingly Philoſophers to the babe Ieſus, I preſent vnto you euen our Lord Ieſus himſelfe, whoſe infinit value is not to be comprehended within the weake imagination or wit of man: and as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> gaue health to the body, ſo I deliuer you the health of the ſoule; which is this moſt pretious pearle of all perfection, this rich diamond of deuotion, this perfect gold growing in the veins of that excellent earth of the moſt bleſſed Paradice, wherein our ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> had his reſtleſſe habitation. The ſweet incenſe, balſums, odours, and gummes that flowes from that beautifull tree of Life, ſprung from the roote of <hi>Ieſſie,</hi> which is ſo ſuper-excellent, that it giueth grace to the meaneſt &amp; moſt vnworthy hand that will vndertake to write thereof; neither can it receiue any blemiſh thereby: for as a right diamond can looſe no whit of his beautie by the blacke foyle vnderneath it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by beeing placed in the darke, but retaines his naturall beauty and brightneſſe ſhining in greater perfection than before; ſo this moſt pretious diamond, for beauty and riches exceeding all the moſt pretious diamonds and rich jewels of the world, can receiue no blemiſh, nor impeachment, by
<pb facs="tcp:29214:17"/>my vnworthy hand writing; but wil with the Sunne retaine his owne brightneſſe and moſt glorious luſtre, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo many blind eyes looke vpon him. Therefore good Madame, to the moſt perfect eyes of your vnderſtanding, I deliuer the ineſtinable treaſure of all elected ſoules, to bee peruſed at conuenient times; as alſo, the mirrour of your moſt worthy minde, which may remaine in the world ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares longer than your Honour, or my ſelfe can liue, to be a light vnto thoſe that come after, deſiring to tread in the narrow path of virtue, that leads the way to heauen. In which way, I pray God ſend your Honour long to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, that your light may ſo ſhine before men, that they may glorifie your father which is in Heauen: and that I and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others may follow you in the ſame tracke. So wiſhing you in this world all increaſe of health and honour, and in the world to come life euerlaſting, I reſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:17"/>
            <head>¶ To the Ladie <hi>Katherine</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe <hi>of Suffolke.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ALthough great Lady, it may ſeeme right ſtrange,</l>
               <l>That I a ſtranger ſhould preſume thus farre,</l>
               <l>To write to you; yet as the times doe change,</l>
               <l>So are we ſubiect to that fatall ſtarre,</l>
               <l>Vnder the which we were produc'd to breath,</l>
               <l>That ſtarre that guides vs euen vntill our death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And guided me to frame this worke of grace,</l>
               <l>Not of it ſelfe, but by celeſtiall powres,</l>
               <l>To which, both that and wee muſt needs giue place,</l>
               <l>Since what we haue, we cannot count it ours:</l>
               <l>For health, wealth, honour, ſickeneſſe, death &amp; all,</l>
               <l>Is in Gods powre, which makes vs riſe and fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſince his powre hath giuen me powre to write,</l>
               <l>A ſubiect ſit for you to looke vpon,</l>
               <l>Wherein your ſoule may take no ſmall delight,</l>
               <l>When her bright eyes beholds that holy one:</l>
               <l>By whoſe great wiſedome, loue, and ſpeciall grace,</l>
               <l>Shee was created to behold his face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vouchſafe ſweet Lady, to accept theſe lines,</l>
               <l>Writ by a hand that doth deſire to doe</l>
               <l>All ſeruices to you whoſe worth combines</l>
               <l>The worthi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt minds to loue and honour you:</l>
               <l>Whoſe beautie, wiſedome, children, high eſtate,</l>
               <l>Doe all concurre to make you fortunate.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:18"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But chiefly your moſt honorable Lord,</l>
               <l>Whoſe noble virtues Fame can ne'r forget:</l>
               <l>His hand being alwayes ready to afford</l>
               <l>Help to the weake, to the vnfortunate:</l>
               <l>All which begets more honour and respect,</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Croeſſus</hi> wealth, or <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſterne aspect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And rightly ſheweth that hee is deſcended</l>
               <l>Of honourable <hi>Howards</hi> antient houſe;</l>
               <l>Whoſe noble deedes by former times commended,</l>
               <l>Do now remaine in your moſt loyall Spouſe,</l>
               <l>On whom God powres all bleſſings from aboue,</l>
               <l>Wealth, honour, children and a worthy Loue;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which is more deare to him than all the reſt,</l>
               <l>You being the louing Hinde and pleaſant Roe,</l>
               <l>Wife of his youth, in whom his ſoule is bleſt,</l>
               <l>Fountaine from whence his chiefe delights do flow.</l>
               <l>Faire tree from which the fruit of Honor ſprings,</l>
               <l>Heere I preſent to you the King of kings:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deſiring you to take a perfit view,</l>
               <l>Of thoſe great torments Patience did indure;</l>
               <l>And reape thoſe Comforts that belongs to you,</l>
               <l>Which his most painfull death did then aſſure:</l>
               <l>Writing the Couenant with his pretious blood,</l>
               <l>That your faire ſoule might bathe her in that flood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And let your noble daughters likewiſe reade</l>
               <l>This little Booke that I preſent to you;</l>
               <l>On heauenly food let them vouchſafe to feede;</l>
               <l>Heere they may ſee a Louer much more true</l>
               <l>Than euer was ſince first the world began,</l>
               <l>This poore rich King that di'd both God and man.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:18"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea, let thoſe Ladies which do repreſent</l>
               <l>All beauty, wiſedome, zeale, and loue,</l>
               <l>Receiue this iewell from <hi>Iehoua</hi> ſent,</l>
               <l>This ſpotleſſe Lambe, this perfit patient Doue:</l>
               <l>Of whom faire <hi>Gabriel,</hi> Gods bright <hi>Mercury,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Brought downe a meſſage from the Deitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here may they ſee him in a flood of teares,</l>
               <l>Crowned with thornes, and bathing in his blood;</l>
               <l>Here may they ſee his feares exceed all feares,</l>
               <l>When Heauen in Iuſtice flat againſt him ſtood:</l>
               <l>And loathſome death with grim and gaſtly look,</l>
               <l>Preſented him that blacke infernall booke,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherein the ſinnes of all the world were writ,</l>
               <l>In deepe Characters of due puniſhment;</l>
               <l>And naught but dying breath could cancel it:</l>
               <l>Shame, death, and hell muſt make the attonement:</l>
               <l>Shewing their euidence, ſeizing wrongful Right,</l>
               <l>Placing heau'ns Beauty in deaths darkeſt night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet through the ſable Clowdes of Shame &amp; Death,</l>
               <l>His beauty ſhewes more clearer than before;</l>
               <l>Death loſt his ſtrength when he did looſe his breath:</l>
               <l>As fire ſuppreſt doth ſhine and flame the more,</l>
               <l>So in Deaths aſhie pale diſcoloured face,</l>
               <l>Freſh beauty ſhin'd, yeelding farre greater grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No Doue, no Swan, nor Iu'rie could compare</l>
               <l>With this faire corps, when 'twas by death imbrac'd;</l>
               <l>No roſe, nor no vermillion halfe ſo faire</l>
               <l>As was that pretious blood that iuterlac'd</l>
               <l>His body, which bright Angels did attend,</l>
               <l>Waiting on him that muſt to Heauen aſcend.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>In whom is all that Ladies can deſire;</l>
               <l>If Beauty, who hath bin more faire than he?</l>
               <l>If Wiſedome, doth not all the world admire</l>
               <l>The depth of his, that cannot ſearched be?</l>
               <l>If wealth, if honour, fame, or Kingdoms ſtore,</l>
               <l>Who euer liu'd that was poſſeſt of more?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If zeale, if grace, if loue, if pietie,</l>
               <l>If conſtancie, if faith, if faire obedience,</l>
               <l>If valour, patience, or ſobrietie;</l>
               <l>If chaſt behauiour, meekeneſſe, continence,</l>
               <l>If iuſtice, mercie, bountie, charitie,</l>
               <l>Who can compare with his Diuinitie?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe vertues more than thoughts can apprehend,</l>
               <l>I leaue to their more cleere imagination,</l>
               <l>That will vouchſafe their borrowed time to ſpend</l>
               <l>In meditating, and in contemplation</l>
               <l>Of his rare parts, true honours faire proſpect,</l>
               <l>The perfect line that goodneſſe doth direct.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And vnto you I wiſh thoſe ſweet deſires,</l>
               <l>That from your perfect thoughts doe daily ſpring,</l>
               <l>Increaſing ſtill pure, bright, and holy fires,</l>
               <l>Which ſparkes of pretious grace, by faith doe ſpring:</l>
               <l>Mounting your ſoule vnto eternall reſt,</l>
               <l>There to liue happily among the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:19"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Ladie ANNE, <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſse of Dorcet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you I dedicate this worke of Grace,</l>
               <l>This frame of Glory which I haue erected,</l>
               <l>For your faire mind I hold the fitteſt place,</l>
               <l>Where virtue ſhould be fetled &amp; protected;</l>
               <l>If higheſt thoughts true honor do imbrace,</l>
               <l>And holy Wiſdom is of them reſpected:</l>
               <l>Then in this Mirrour let your faire eyes looke,</l>
               <l>To view your virtues in this bleſſed Booke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bleſt by our Sauiours merits, not my skil,</l>
               <l>Which I acknowledge to be very ſmall;</l>
               <l>Yet if the leaſt part of his bleſſed Will</l>
               <l>I haue perform'd, I count I haue done all:</l>
               <l>One ſparke of grace ſufficient is to fill</l>
               <l>Our Lampes with oyle, ready when he doth call</l>
               <l>To enter with the Bridegroome to the feaſt,</l>
               <l>Where he that is the greateſt may be leaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Greatneſſe is no ſure frame to build vpon,</l>
               <l>No worldly treaſure can aſſure that place;</l>
               <l>God makes both euen, the Cottage with the Throne,</l>
               <l>All worldly honours there are counted baſe;</l>
               <l>Thoſe he holds deare, and reckneth as his owne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe virtuous deeds by his eſpecially grace</l>
               <l>Haue gain'd his loue, his kingdome, and his crowne,</l>
               <l>Whom in the booke of Life he hath ſet downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Titles of honour which the world beſtowes,</l>
               <l>To none but to the virtuous doth belong;</l>
               <l>As beauteous bowres where true worth ſhould repoſe,</l>
               <l>And where his dwellings ſhould be built moſt ſtrong:</l>
               <l>But when they are beſtow'd vpon her foes,</l>
               <l>Poore virtues friends indure the greateſt wrong:</l>
               <l>For they muſt fuffer all indignity,</l>
               <l>Vntill in heau'n they better graced be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What difference was there when the world began,</l>
               <l>Was it not Virtue that diſtinguiſht all?</l>
               <l>All ſprang but from one woman and one man,</l>
               <l>Then how doth Gentry come to riſe and fall?</l>
               <l>Or who is he that very rightly can</l>
               <l>Diſtinguiſh of his birth, or tell at all,</l>
               <l>In what meane ſtate his Anceſtors haue bin,</l>
               <l>Before ſome one of worth did honour win?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe ſucceſſors, although they beare his name,</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſing not the riches of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inde,</l>
               <l>How doe we know they ſpring out of the ſame</l>
               <l>True ſtocke of honour, beeing not of that ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d?</l>
               <l>It is faire virtue gets immortall fame,</l>
               <l>Tis that doth all loue and duty bind:</l>
               <l>If he that much enjoyes, doth little good,</l>
               <l>We may ſuppoſe he comes not of that blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor is he fit for honour, or command,</l>
               <l>If baſe affections ouer-rules his mind;</l>
               <l>Or that ſelfe-will doth carry ſuch a hand,</l>
               <l>As worldly pleaſures haue the powre to blind</l>
               <l>So as he cannot ſee, nor vnderſtand</l>
               <l>How to diſcharge that place to him affign'd:</l>
               <l>Gods Stewards muſt for all the poore prouide,</l>
               <l>If in Gods houſe they purpoſe to abide.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>To you, as to Gods Steward I doe write,</l>
               <l>In whom the ſeeds of virtue haue bin ſowne,</l>
               <l>By your moſt worthy mother, in whoſe right,</l>
               <l>All her faire parts you challenge as your owne;</l>
               <l>If you, ſweet Lady, will appeare as bright</l>
               <l>As euer creature did that time hath knowne,</l>
               <l>Then weare this Diadem I preſent to thee,</l>
               <l>Which I haue fram'd for her Eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You are the Heire apparant of this Crowne</l>
               <l>Of goodneſſe, bountie, grace, loue, pietie,</l>
               <l>By birth its yours, then keepe it as your owne,</l>
               <l>Defend it from all baſe indignitie;</l>
               <l>The right your Mother hath to it, is knowne</l>
               <l>Beſt vnto you, who reapt ſuch fruit thereby:</l>
               <l>This Monument of her faire worth retaine</l>
               <l>In your pure mind, and keepe it from al ſtaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as your Anceſtors at firſt poſſeſt</l>
               <l>Their honours, for their honourable deeds,</l>
               <l>Let their faire virtues neuer be tranſgreſt,</l>
               <l>Bind vp the broken, ſtop the wounds that bleeds,</l>
               <l>Succour the poore, comfort the comfortleſſe,</l>
               <l>Cheriſh faire plants, ſuppreſſe vnwholſom weeds;</l>
               <l>Although baſe pelfe do chance to come in place,</l>
               <l>Yet let true worth receiue your greateſt grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So ſhal you ſhew from whence you are deſcended,</l>
               <l>And leaue to all poſterities your fame,</l>
               <l>So will your virtues alwaies be commended,</l>
               <l>And euery one will reuerence your name;</l>
               <l>So this poore worke of mine ſhalbe defended</l>
               <l>From any ſcandall that the world can frame:</l>
               <l>And you a glorious Actor will appeare</l>
               <l>Louely to all, but vnto God moſt deare.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>I know right well theſe are but needleſſe lines,</l>
               <l>To you, that are ſo perfect in your part,</l>
               <l>Whoſe birth and education both combines;</l>
               <l>Nay more than both, a pure and godly heart,</l>
               <l>So well inſtructed to ſuch faire deſignes,</l>
               <l>By your deere Mother, that there needs no art:</l>
               <l>Your ripe diſcretion in your tender yeares,</l>
               <l>By all your actions to the world appeares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I doe but ſet a candle in the ſunne,</l>
               <l>And adde one drop of water to the ſea,</l>
               <l>Virtue and Beautie both together run,</l>
               <l>When you were borne, within your breaſt to ſtay;</l>
               <l>Their quarrell ceaſt, which long before begun,</l>
               <l>They liue in peace, and all doe them obey:</l>
               <l>In you faire Madame, are they richly plac'd,</l>
               <l>Where all their worth by Eternity is grac'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You goddeſſe-like vnto the world appeare,</l>
               <l>Inricht with more than fortune can beſtowe,</l>
               <l>Goodneſſe and Grace, which you doe hold more deere</l>
               <l>Than worldly wealth, which melts away like ſnowe;</l>
               <l>Your pleaſure is the word of God to heare,</l>
               <l>That his moſt holy precepts you may know:</l>
               <l>Your greateſt honour, faire and virtuous deeds,</l>
               <l>Which from the loue and feare of God proceeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore to you (good Madame) I preſent</l>
               <l>His louely loue, more worth than pureſt gold,</l>
               <l>Who for your ſake his pretious blood hath ſpent,</l>
               <l>His death and paſſion here you may behold,</l>
               <l>And view this Lambe, that to the world was ſent,</l>
               <l>Whom your faire ſoule may in her armes infold:</l>
               <l>Louing his loue, that did endure ſuch paine,</l>
               <l>That you in heauen a worthy place might gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>For well you knowe, this world is but a Stage</l>
               <l>Where all doe play their parts, and muſt be gone;</l>
               <l>Here's no reſpect of perſons, youth, nor age,</l>
               <l>Death ſeizeth all, he neuer ſpareth one,</l>
               <l>None can preuent or ſtay that tyrants rage,</l>
               <l>But Ieſus Chriſt the Iuſt: By him alone</l>
               <l>He was orecome, He open ſet the dore</l>
               <l>To Eternall life, ne're ſeene, nor knowne before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He is the ſtone the builders did refuſe,</l>
               <l>Which you, ſweet Lady, are to build vpon;</l>
               <l>He is the rocke that holy Church did chuſe,</l>
               <l>Among which number, you muſt needs be one;</l>
               <l>Faire Shepheardeſſe, tis you that he will vſe</l>
               <l>To feed his flocke, that truſt in him alone:</l>
               <l>All wordly bleſſings he vouchſafes to you,</l>
               <l>That to the poore you may returne his due.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if deſerts a Ladies loue may gaine,</l>
               <l>Then tell me, who hath more deſeru'd than he?</l>
               <l>Therefore in recompence of all his paine,</l>
               <l>Beſtowe your paines to reade, and pardon me,</l>
               <l>If out of wants, or weakeneſſe of my braine,</l>
               <l>I haue not done this worke ſufficiently;</l>
               <l>Yet lodge him in the cloſet of your heart,</l>
               <l>Whoſe worth is more than can be ſhew'd by Art.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_virtuous_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:22"/>
            <head>TO THE VERTVOVS Reader.</head>
            <p>OFten haue I heard, that it is the property of ſome wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, not only to emulate the virtues and perfections of the reſt, but alſo by all their powers of ill ſpeaking, to ecclipſe the brightnes of their deſerued fame: now contrary to this cuſtome, which men I hope vniuſtly lay to their charge, I haue written this ſmall volume, or little booke, for the generall vſe of all virtuous Ladies and Gentlewomen of this kingdome; and in commendation of ſome particular perſons of our owne ſexe, ſuch as for the moſt part, are ſo well knowne to my ſelfe, and others, that I dare vndertake Fame dares not to call any better. And this haue I done, to make knowne to the world, that all women deſerue not to be blamed though ſome forgetting they are women themſelues, and in danger to be condemned by the words of their owne mouthes, fall into ſo great an errour, as to ſpeake vnaduiſedly againſt the reſt of their ſexe; which if it be true, I am perſwaded they can ſhew their owne imperfection in nothing more: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could wiſh (for their owne eaſe, modeſties, and credit) they would referre ſuch points of folly, to be practiſed by euill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed men, who forgetting they were borne of women, nouriſhed of women, and that if it were not by the means of women, they would be quite extinguiſhed out of the world, and a finall ende of them all, doe like Vipers deface the wombes wherein they were bred, onely to giue way and vtterance to their want of diſcretion and goodneſſe. Such as theſe, were they that diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Chriſt his Apoſtles and Prophets, putting them to ſhamefull deaths. Therefore we are not to regard any imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that they vndeſeruedly lay vpon vs, no otherwiſe than to make vſe of them to our owne benefits, as ſpurres to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, making vs flie all occaſions that may colour their vniuſt
<pb facs="tcp:29214:23"/>ſpeeches to paſſe currant. Eſpecially conſidering that they haue tempted euen the patience of God himſelfe, who gaue power to wiſe and virtuous women, to bring downe their pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie. As was cruell <hi>Ceſarus</hi> by the diſcreet counſell of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Deborah,</hi> Iudge and Propheteſſe of Iſrael: and reſolution of <hi>Iael</hi> wife of <hi>Heber</hi> the Kenite: wicked <hi>Haman,</hi> by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine prayers and prudent proceedings of beautifull <hi>Heſter:</hi> blaſphemous <hi>Holofernes,</hi> by the inuincible courage, rare wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and confident carriage of <hi>Iudeth:</hi> &amp; the vniuſt Indges, by the innocency of chaſt <hi>Suſanna:</hi> with infinite others, which for breuitie ſake I will omit. As alſo in reſpect it pleaſed our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, without the aſſiſtance of man, beeing free from originall and all other ſinnes, from the time of his conception, till the houre of his death, to be begotten of a woman, borne of a woman, nouriſhed of a woman, obedient to a woman; and that he healed woman, pardoned women, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted women: yea, euen when he was in his greateſt agonie and bloodie ſweat, going to be crucified, and alſo in the laſt houre of his death, tooke care to diſpoſe of a woman: after his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, appeared firſt to a woman, ſent a woman to declare his moſt glorious reſurrection to the reſt of his Diſciples. Many other examples I could alleadge of diuers faithfull and virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous women, who haue in all ages, not onely beene Confeſſors, but alſo indured moſt cruel martyrdome for their faith in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. All which is ſufficient to inforce all good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and honourable minded men to ſpeake reuerently of our ſexe, and eſpecially of all virtuous and good women. To the modeſt ſenſures of both which, I refer theſe my imperfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, knowing that according to their owne excellent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſitions, they will rather, cheriſh, nouriſh, and increaſe the leaſt ſparke of virtue where they find it, by their fauourable and beſt interpretations, than quench it by wrong conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. To whom I wiſh all increaſe of virtue, and deſire their beſt opinions.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:23"/>
            <head>Salue Deus Rex Iudaeorum.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SIth <hi>Cynthia</hi> is aſcended to that reſt</l>
               <l>Of endleſſe joy and true Eternitie,</l>
               <l>That glorious place that cannot be expreſt</l>
               <l>By any wight clad in mortalitie,</l>
               <l>In her almightie love ſo highly bleſt,</l>
               <l>And crown'd with everlaſting Sov'raigntie;</l>
               <l>Where Saints and Angells do attend her Throne,</l>
               <l>And ſhe gives glorie vnto God alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Ladie Margaret Counteſſe Dowager of Cumberland</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ To thee great Counteſſe now I will applie</l>
                  <l>My Pen, to write thy never dying fame;</l>
                  <l>That when to Heav'n thy bleſſed Soule ſhall flie,</l>
                  <l>Theſe lines on earth record thy reverend name:</l>
                  <l>And to this taske I meane my Muſe to tie,</l>
                  <l>Though wanting skill I ſhall but purchaſe blame:</l>
                  <l>Pardon (deere Ladie) want of womans wit</l>
                  <l>To pen thy praiſe, when few can equall it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And pardon (Madame) though I do not write</l>
                  <l>Thoſe praiſefull lines of that delightfull place,</l>
                  <l>As you commaunded me in that faire night,</l>
                  <l>When ſhining <hi>Phoebe</hi> gave ſo great a grace,</l>
                  <l>Preſenting <hi>Paradice</hi> to your ſweet ſight,</l>
                  <l>Vnfolding all the beauty of her face</l>
                  <l>With pleaſant groves, hills, walks and ſtately trees,</l>
                  <l>Which pleaſures with retired minds agrees.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:24"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe Eagles eyes behold the glorious Sunne</l>
                  <l>Of th'all-creating Providence, reflecting</l>
                  <l>His bleſſed beames on all by him, begunne;</l>
                  <l>Increaſing, ſtrengthning, guiding and directing</l>
                  <l>All worldly creatures their due courſe to runne,</l>
                  <l>Vnto His powrefull pleaſure all ſubjecting:</l>
                  <l>And thou (deere Ladie) by his ſpeciall grace,</l>
                  <l>In theſe his creatures doſt behold his face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe all-reviving beautie, yeelds ſuch joyes</l>
                  <l>To thy ſad Soule, plunged in waves of woe,</l>
                  <l>That worldly pleaſures ſeemes to thee as toyes,</l>
                  <l>Onely thou ſeek'ſt Eternitie to know,</l>
                  <l>Reſpecting not the infinite annoyes</l>
                  <l>That Satan to thy well-ſtaid mind can ſhow;</l>
                  <l>Ne can he quench in thee, the Spirit of Grace,</l>
                  <l>Nor draw thee from beholding Heavens bright face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy Mind ſo perfect by thy Maker fram'd,</l>
                  <l>No vaine delights can harbour in thy heart,</l>
                  <l>With his ſweet love, thou art ſo much inflam'd,</l>
                  <l>As of the world thou ſeem'ſt to have no part;</l>
                  <l>So, love him ſtill, thou need'ſt not be aſham'd,</l>
                  <l>Tis He that made thee, what thou wert, and art:</l>
                  <l>Tis He that dries all teares from Orphans eies,</l>
                  <l>And heares from he av'n the wofull widdows cries.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tis He that doth behold thy inward cares,</l>
                  <l>And will regard the ſorrowes of thy Soule;</l>
                  <l>Tis He that guides thy feet from Sathans ſnares,</l>
                  <l>And in his Wiſedome, doth thy waies controule:</l>
                  <l>He through afflictions, ſtill thy Minde prepares,</l>
                  <l>And all thy glorious Trialls will enroule:</l>
                  <l>That when darke daies of terror ſhall appeare,</l>
                  <l>Thou as the Sunne ſhalt ſhine; or much more cleare.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:24"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Heav'ns ſhall periſh as a garment olde,</l>
                  <l>Or as a veſture by the maker chang'd,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall depart, as when a skrowle is rolde;</l>
                  <l>Yet thou from him ſhalt neuer be eſtrang'd,</l>
                  <l>When He ſhall come in glory, that was ſolde</l>
                  <l>For all our ſnnes; we happily are chang'd,</l>
                  <l>Who for our faults put on his righteouſneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Although full oft his Lawes we doe tranſgreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Long mai'ſt thou joy in this almightie love,</l>
                  <l>Long may thy Soule be pleaſing in his ſight,</l>
                  <l>Long mai'ſt thou have true comforts from above,</l>
                  <l>Long mai'ſt thou ſet on him thy whole delight,</l>
                  <l>And patiently endure when he doth proue,</l>
                  <l>Knowing that He will ſurely do thee right:</l>
                  <l>Thy patience, faith, long ſuffring, and thy love,</l>
                  <l>He will reward with comforts from above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With Majeſtie and Honour is He clad,</l>
                  <l>And deck'd with light, as with a garment faire;</l>
                  <l>He joyes the Meeke, and makes the Mightie ſad,</l>
                  <l>Pulls downe the Prowd, and doth the Humble reare:</l>
                  <l>Who ſees this Bridegroome, never can be ſad;</l>
                  <l>None lives that can his wondrous workes declare:</l>
                  <l>Yea, looke how farre the Eſt is from the Weſt,</l>
                  <l>So farre he ſets our ſinnes that have tranſgreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He rides vpon the wings of all the windes,</l>
                  <l>And ſpreads the heav'ns with his all powrefull hand;</l>
                  <l>Oh! who can looſe when the Almightie bindes?</l>
                  <l>Or in his angry preſence dares to ſtand?</l>
                  <l>He ſearcheth out the ſecrets of all mindes;</l>
                  <l>All thoſe that feare him ſhall poſſeſſe the Land:</l>
                  <l>He is exceeding glorious to behold,</l>
                  <l>Antient of Times; ſo faire, and yet ſo old.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:25"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>He of the watry Cloudes his Chariot frames,</l>
                  <l>And makes his bleſſed Angels powrefull Spirits,</l>
                  <l>His Miniſters are fearefull fiery flames,</l>
                  <l>Rewarding all according to their merits;</l>
                  <l>The Righteous for an heritage he claimes,</l>
                  <l>And regiſters the wrongs of humble ſpirits:</l>
                  <l>Hills melt like wax, in preſence of the Lord,</l>
                  <l>So do all ſinners, in his ſight abhorr'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He in the waters laies his chamber beames,</l>
                  <l>And cloudes of darkeneſſe compaſſe him about,</l>
                  <l>Conſuming fire ſhall goe before in ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>And burne vp all his en'mies round about:</l>
                  <l>Yet on theſe Iudgementsw orldlings never dreames,</l>
                  <l>Nor of theſe daungers never ſtand in doubt:</l>
                  <l>While he ſhall reſt within his holy Hill,</l>
                  <l>That lives and dies according to his Will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But woe to them that double-hearted bee,</l>
                  <l>Who with their tongues the righteous Soules doe ſlay;</l>
                  <l>Bending their bowes to ſhoot at all they ſee,</l>
                  <l>With vpright hearts their Maker to obay;</l>
                  <l>And ſecretly doe let their arrowes flee,</l>
                  <l>To wound true hearted people any way:</l>
                  <l>The Lord wil roote them out that ſpeake prowd things,</l>
                  <l>Deceitfull tongues are but falſe Slanders wings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Froward are the vngodly from their berth,</l>
                  <l>No ſooner borne, but they doe goe aſtray;</l>
                  <l>The Lord will roote them out from off the earth,</l>
                  <l>And give them to their en'mies for a pray,</l>
                  <l>As venemous as Serpents is their breath,</l>
                  <l>With poyſned lies to hurt in what they may</l>
                  <l>The Innocent: who as a Dove ſhall flie</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Lord, that he his cauſe may trie.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:25"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The righteous Lord doth righteouſneſſe allow,</l>
                  <l>His countenance will behold the thing that's juſt;</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Meane he makes the Mightie bow,</l>
                  <l>And raiſeth vp the Poore out of the duſt:</l>
                  <l>Yet makes no count to vs, nor when, nor how,</l>
                  <l>But powres his grace on all, that puts their truſt</l>
                  <l>In him: that never will their hopes betray,</l>
                  <l>Nor lets them periſh that for mercie pray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He ſhall within his Tabernacle dwell,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe life is vncorrupt before the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Who no vntrueths of Innocents doth tell,</l>
                  <l>Nor wrongs his neighbour, nor in deed, nor word,</l>
                  <l>Nor in his pride with malice ſeems to ſwell,</l>
                  <l>Nor whets his tongue more ſharper than a ſword,</l>
                  <l>To wound the reputation of the Iuſt;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſeekes to lay their glorie in the Duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That great <hi>Iehova</hi> King of heav'n and earth,</l>
                  <l>Will raine downe fire and brimſtone from above,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the wicked monſters in their berth</l>
                  <l>That ſtorme and rage at thoſe whom he doth love:</l>
                  <l>Snares, ſtormes, and tempeſts he will raine, and dearth,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he will himſelfe almightie prove:</l>
                  <l>And this ſhall be their portion they ſhall drinke,</l>
                  <l>That thinkes the Lord is blind when he doth winke.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Pardon (good Madame) though I have digreſt</l>
                  <l>From what I doc intend to write of thee,</l>
                  <l>To ſet his glorie forth whom thou lov'ſt beſt,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wondrous works no mortall eie can ſee;</l>
                  <l>His ſpeciall care on thoſe whom he hath bleſt</l>
                  <l>From wicked worldlings, how he ſets them free:</l>
                  <l>And how ſuch people he doth overthrow</l>
                  <l>In all their waies, that they his powre may know.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:26"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The meditation of this Monarchs love,</l>
                  <l>Drawes thee from caring what this world can yield;</l>
                  <l>Of joyes and griefes both equall thou doſt prove,</l>
                  <l>They have no force, to force thee from the field:</l>
                  <l>Thy conſtant faith like to the Turtle Dove</l>
                  <l>Continues combat, and will never yield</l>
                  <l>To baſe affliction; or prowd pomps deſire,</l>
                  <l>That ſets the weakeſt mindes ſo much on fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou from the Court to the Countrie art retir'd,</l>
                  <l>Leaving the world, before the world leaves thee:</l>
                  <l>That great Enchantreſſe of weake mindes admir'd,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe all-bewitching charmes ſo pleaſing be</l>
                  <l>To worldly wantons; and too much deſir'd</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe that care not for Eternitie:</l>
                  <l>But yeeld themſelves as preys to Luſt and Sinne,</l>
                  <l>Looſing their hopes of Heav'n Hell paines to winne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But thou, the wonder of our wanton age</l>
                  <l>Leav'ſt all delights to ſerve a heav'nly King:</l>
                  <l>Who is more wiſe? or who can be more ſage,</l>
                  <l>Than ſhe that doth Affection ſubject bring;</l>
                  <l>Not forcing for the world, or Satans rage,</l>
                  <l>But ſhrowding vnder the Almighties wing;</l>
                  <l>Spending her yeares, moneths, daies, minutes, howres,</l>
                  <l>In doing ſervice to the heav'nly powres.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou faire example, live without compare,</l>
                  <l>With Honours triumphs ſeated in thy breaſt;</l>
                  <l>Pale Envy never can thy name empaire,</l>
                  <l>When in thy heart thou harbour'ſt ſuch a gueſt:</l>
                  <l>Malice muſt live for ever in diſpaire;</l>
                  <l>There's no revenge where Virtue ſtill doth reſt:</l>
                  <l>All hearts muſt needs do homage vnto thee,</l>
                  <l>In whom all eies ſuch rare perfection ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:26"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>That outward Beautie which the world commends,
<note place="margin">An Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive against outward beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vnaccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with virtue.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is not the ſubject I will write vpon,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe date expir'd, that tyrant Time ſoone ends,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe gawdie colours ſoone are ſpent and gone:</l>
                  <l>But thoſe faire Virtues which on thee attends</l>
                  <l>Are alwaies freſh, they never are but one:</l>
                  <l>They make thy Beautie fairer to behold,</l>
                  <l>Than was that Queenes for whom prowd <hi>Troy</hi> was ſold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As for thoſe matchleſſe colours Red and White,</l>
                  <l>Or perfit features in a fading face,</l>
                  <l>Or due proportion pleaſing to the ſight;</l>
                  <l>All theſe doe draw but dangers and diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>A mind enrich'd with Virtue, ſhines more bright,</l>
                  <l>Addes everlaſting Beauty, gives true grace,</l>
                  <l>Frames an immortall Goddeſſe on the earth,</l>
                  <l>Who though ſhe dies; yet Fame gives her new berth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That pride of Nature which adornes the faire,</l>
                  <l>Like blaſing Comets to allure all eies,</l>
                  <l>Is but the thred, that weaves their web of Care,</l>
                  <l>Who glories moſt, where moſt their danger lies;</l>
                  <l>For greateſt perills do attend the faire,</l>
                  <l>When men do ſeeke, attempt, plot and deviſe,</l>
                  <l>How they may overthrow the chaſteſt Dame,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Beautie is the White whereat they aime.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Twas Beautie bred in <hi>Troy</hi> the ten yeares ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>And carried <hi>Hellen</hi> from her lawfull Lord;</l>
                  <l>Twas Beautie made chaſte <hi>Lucrece</hi> looſe her life,</l>
                  <l>For which prowd <hi>Tarquins</hi> fact was ſo abhorr'd:</l>
                  <l>Beautie the cauſe <hi>Antonius</hi> wrong'd his wife,</l>
                  <l>Which could not be decided but by ſword:</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Cleopatraes</hi> Beautie and defects</l>
                  <l>Did worke <hi>Octaviaes</hi> wrongs, and his neglects.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:27"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>What fruit did yeeld that faire forbidden tree,</l>
                  <l>But blood, diſhonour, infamie, and ſhame?</l>
                  <l>Poore blinded Queene, could'ſt thou no better ſee,</l>
                  <l>But entertaine diſgrace, in ſtead of fame?</l>
                  <l>Doe theſe deſignes with Maieſtie agree?</l>
                  <l>To ſtaine thy blood, and blot thy royall name.</l>
                  <l>That heart that gave conſent vnto this ill,</l>
                  <l>Did give conſent that thou thy ſelfe ſhould'ſt kill.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Roſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Faire <hi>Roſamund,</hi> the wonder of her time,</l>
                  <l>Had bin much fairer, had ſhee not bin faire;</l>
                  <l>Beautie betraid her thoughts, aloft to clime,</l>
                  <l>To build ſtrong caſtles in vncertaine aire,</l>
                  <l>Where th'infection of a wanton crime</l>
                  <l>Did worke her fall; firſt poyſon, then deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>With double death did kill her periur'd ſoule,</l>
                  <l>When heauenly Iuſtice did her ſinne controule.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Matilda.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Holy <hi>Matilda</hi> in a hapleſſe houre</l>
                  <l>Was borne to ſorow and to diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Beauty the cauſe that turn'd her Sweet to Sowre,</l>
                  <l>While Chaſtity ſought Folly to preuent.</l>
                  <l>Luſtfull King <hi>Iohn</hi> refus'd, did vſe his powre,</l>
                  <l>By Fire and Sword, to compaſſe his content:</l>
                  <l>But Friends diſgrace, nor Fathers baniſhment,</l>
                  <l>Nor Death it ſelfe, could purchaſe her conſent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here Beauty in the height of all perfection,</l>
                  <l>Crown'd this faire Creatures euerlaſting fame,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe noble minde did ſcorne the baſe ſubiection</l>
                  <l>Of Feares, or Fauours, to impaire her Name:</l>
                  <l>By heauenly grace, ſhe had ſuch true direction,</l>
                  <l>To die with Honour, not to liue in Shame;</l>
                  <l>And drinke that poyſon with a cheerefull heart,</l>
                  <l>That could all Heavenly grace to her impart.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Ladie of Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction to the paſſion of Christ.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:27"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ This Grace great Lady, doth poſſeſſe thy Soule,</l>
                  <l>And makes thee pleaſing in thy Makers ſight;</l>
                  <l>This Grace doth all imperfect Thoughts controule,</l>
                  <l>Directing thee to ſerue thy God aright;</l>
                  <l>Still reckoning him, the Husband of thy Soule,</l>
                  <l>Which is moſt pretious in his glorious ſight:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the Worlds delights ſhee doth denie</l>
                  <l>For him, who for her ſake vouchſaf'd to die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And dying made her Dowager of all;</l>
                  <l>Nay more, Co-heire of that eternall bliſſe</l>
                  <l>That Angels loſt, and We by <hi>Adams</hi> fall;</l>
                  <l>Meere Caſt-awaies, rais'd by a <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſe,</l>
                  <l>Chriſts bloody ſweat, the Vineger, and Gall,</l>
                  <l>The Speare, Sponge, Nailes, his buffeting with Fiſts,</l>
                  <l>His bitter Paſſion, Agony, and Death,</l>
                  <l>Did gaine vs Heauen when He did looſe his breath.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A preamble of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor before the Paſſion.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Theſe high deſerts inuites my lowely Muſe</l>
                  <l>To write of Him, and pardon craue of thee,</l>
                  <l>For Time ſo ſpent, I need make no excuſe,</l>
                  <l>Knowing it doth with thy faire Minde agree</l>
                  <l>So well, as thou no Labour wilt refuſe,</l>
                  <l>That to thy holy Loue may pleaſing be:</l>
                  <l>His Death and Paſſion I deſire to write,</l>
                  <l>And thee to reade, the bleſſed Soules delight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But my deare Muſe, now whither wouldſt thou flie,</l>
                  <l>Aboue the pitch of thy appointed ſtraine?</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Icarus</hi> thou ſeekeſt now to trie,</l>
                  <l>Not waxen wings, but thy poore barren Braine,</l>
                  <l>Which farre too weake, theſe fiely lines deſcrie;</l>
                  <l>Yet cannot this thy forward Mind reſtraine,</l>
                  <l>But thy poore Infant Verſe muſt ſoare aloft,</l>
                  <l>Not fearing threat'ning dangers, happening oft.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:28"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thinke when the eye of Wiſdom ſhall diſcover</l>
                  <l>Thy weakling Muſe to flie, that ſcarce could creepe,</l>
                  <l>And in the Ayre aboue the Clowdes to hover,</l>
                  <l>When better 'twere mued vp, and faſt aſleepe;</l>
                  <l>They'l thinke with <hi>Phaeton,</hi> thou canſt ne'r recover,</l>
                  <l>But helpleſſe with that poore yong Lad to weepe:</l>
                  <l>The little World of thy weake Wit on fire,</l>
                  <l>Where thou wilt periſh in thine owne deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But yet the Weaker thou doeſt ſeeme to be</l>
                  <l>In Sexe, or Sence, the more his Glory ſhines,</l>
                  <l>That doth infuze ſuch powrefull Grace in thee,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew thy Love in theſe few humble Lines;</l>
                  <l>The Widowes Myte, with this may well agree,</l>
                  <l>Her little All more worth than golden mynes,</l>
                  <l>Beeing more deerer to our loving Lord,</l>
                  <l>Than all the wealth that Kingdoms could afford.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore I humbly for his Grace will pray,</l>
                  <l>That he will give me Power and Strength to Write,</l>
                  <l>That what I haue begun, ſo end I may,</l>
                  <l>As his great Glory may appeare more bright;</l>
                  <l>Yea in theſe Lines I may no further ſtray,</l>
                  <l>Than his moſt holy Spirit ſhall giue me Light:</l>
                  <l>That blindeſt Weakeneſſe be not over-bold,</l>
                  <l>The manner of his Paſſion to vnfold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In other Phraſes than may well agree</l>
                  <l>With his pure Doctrine, and moſt holy Writ,</l>
                  <l>That Heavens cleare eye, and all the World may ſee,</l>
                  <l>I ſeeke his Glory, rather than to get</l>
                  <l>The Vulgars breath, the ſeed of Vanitie,</l>
                  <l>Nor Fames lowd Trumpet care I to admit;</l>
                  <l>But rather ſtrive in plaineſt Words to ſhowe,</l>
                  <l>The Matter which I ſeeke to vndergoe.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:28"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Matter farre beyond my barren skill,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew with any Life this map of Death,</l>
                  <l>This Storie; that whole Worlds with Bookes would fill,</l>
                  <l>In theſe few Lines, will put me out of breath,</l>
                  <l>To run ſo ſwiftly vp this mightie Hill,</l>
                  <l>I may behold it with the eye of Faith;</l>
                  <l>But to preſent this pure vnſpotted Lambe,</l>
                  <l>I muſt confeſſe, I farre vnworthy am.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet if he pleaſe t'illuminate my Spirit,</l>
                  <l>And giue me Wiſdom from his holy Hill,</l>
                  <l>That I may Write part of his glorious Merit,</l>
                  <l>If he vouchſafe to guide my Hand and Quill,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew his Death, by which we doe inherit</l>
                  <l>Thoſe endleſſe Ioyes that all our hearts doe fill;</l>
                  <l>Then will I tell of that ſad blacke fac'd Night,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe mourning Mantle covered Heavenly Light.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here begin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the Paſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Christ.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ That very Night our Saviour was betrayd,</l>
                  <l>Oh night! exceeding all the nights of ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>When our moſt bleſſed Lord, although diſmayd,</l>
                  <l>Yet would not he one Minutes reſpite borrow,</l>
                  <l>But to <hi>Mount Oliues</hi> went, though ſore afraid,</l>
                  <l>To welcome Night, and entertaine the Morrow;</l>
                  <l>And as he oft vnto that place did goe,</l>
                  <l>So did he now, to meete his long nurſt woe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He told his deere Diſciples, that they all</l>
                  <l>Should be offended by him that ſelfe night;</l>
                  <l>His Griefe was great, and theirs could not be ſmall,</l>
                  <l>To part from him who was their ſole Delight;</l>
                  <l>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> thought his Faith could neuer fall,</l>
                  <l>No mote could happen in ſo cleare a ſight:</l>
                  <l>Which made him ſay, Though all men were offended,</l>
                  <l>Yet would he never, though his life were ended.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:29"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>But his deare Lord made anſwere, That before</l>
                  <l>The Cocke did crowe, he ſhould deny him thrice;</l>
                  <l>This could not chooſe but grieue him very ſore,</l>
                  <l>That his hot Loue ſhould prooue more cold than Ice,</l>
                  <l>Denying him he did ſo much adore;</l>
                  <l>No imperfection in himſelfe heſpies,</l>
                  <l>But ſaith againe, with him hee'l ſurely die,</l>
                  <l>Rather than his deare Maſter once denie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And all the reſt (did likewiſe ſay the ſame)</l>
                  <l>Of his Diſciples, at that inſtant time;</l>
                  <l>But yet poore <hi>Peter,</hi> he was moſt too blame,</l>
                  <l>That thought aboue them all, by Faith to clime;</l>
                  <l>His forward ſpeech inflicted ſinne and ſhame,</l>
                  <l>When Wiſdoms eyes did looke and checke his crime:</l>
                  <l>Who did foreſee, and told it him before,</l>
                  <l>Yet would he needs auerre it more and more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now went our Lord vnto that holy place,</l>
                  <l>Sweet <hi>Gethſemaine</hi> hallowed by his preſence,</l>
                  <l>That bleſſed Garden, which did now embrace</l>
                  <l>His holy corps, yet could make no defence</l>
                  <l>Againſt thoſe Vipers, obiects of diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Which ſought that pure eternall Loue to quench:</l>
                  <l>Here his Diſciples willed he to ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt he went further, where he meant to pray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>None were admitted with their Lord to goe,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Peter,</hi> and the ſonnes of <hi>Zebed'us,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To them good <hi>Ieſus</hi> opened all his woe,</l>
                  <l>He gaue them leaue his ſorows to diſcuſſe,</l>
                  <l>His deepeſt griefes, he did not ſcorne to ſhowe</l>
                  <l>Theſe three deere friends, ſo much he did intruſt:</l>
                  <l>Beeing ſorowfull, and ouercharg'd with griefe,</l>
                  <l>He told it them, yet look'd for no reliefe.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:29"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sweet Lord, how couldſt thou thus to fleſh and blood</l>
                  <l>Communicate thy griefe? tell of thy woes?</l>
                  <l>Thou knew'ſt they had no powre to doe thee good,</l>
                  <l>But were the cauſe thou muſt endure theſe blowes,</l>
                  <l>Beeing the Scorpions bred in <hi>Adams</hi> mud,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe poys'ned ſinnes did worke among thy foes,</l>
                  <l>To re-ore-charge thy ouer-burd'ned ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Although the ſorowes now they doe condole.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet didſt thou tell them of thy troubled ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Of thy Soules heauineſſe vnto the death,</l>
                  <l>So full of Loue, ſo free wert thou from hate,</l>
                  <l>To bid them ſtay, whoſe ſinnes did ſtop thy breath,</l>
                  <l>When thou wert entring at ſo ſtraite a gate,</l>
                  <l>Yea entring euen into the doore of Death,</l>
                  <l>Thou bidſt them tarry there, and watch with thee,</l>
                  <l>Who from thy pretious blood-ſhed were not free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bidding them tarry, thou didſt further goe,</l>
                  <l>To meet affliction in ſuch gracefull ſort,</l>
                  <l>As might mooue pitie both in friend and foe,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſorowes ſuch, as none could them comport,</l>
                  <l>Such great Indurements who did euer know,</l>
                  <l>When to th'Almighty thou didſt make reſort?</l>
                  <l>And falling on thy face didſt humbly pray,</l>
                  <l>If 'twere his Will that Cup might paſſe away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Saying, Not my will, but thy will Lord be done.</l>
                  <l>When as thou prayedſt an Angel did appeare</l>
                  <l>From Heauen, to comfort thee Gods onely Sonne,</l>
                  <l>That thou thy Suffrings might'ſt the better beare,</l>
                  <l>Beeing in an agony, thy glaſſe neere run,</l>
                  <l>Thou prayedſt more earneſtly, in ſo great feare,</l>
                  <l>That pretious ſweat came trickling to the ground,</l>
                  <l>Like drops of blood thy ſences to confound.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:30"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe here his Will, not thy Will, Lord, was done,</l>
                  <l>And thou content to vndergoe all paines;</l>
                  <l>Sweet Lambe of God, his deare beloved Sonne,</l>
                  <l>By this great purchaſe, what to thee remaines?</l>
                  <l>Of Heaven and Earth thou haſt a Kingdom wonne,</l>
                  <l>Thy Glory beeing equall with thy Gaines,</l>
                  <l>In ratifying Gods promiſe on th'earth,</l>
                  <l>Made many hundred yeares before thy berth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now returning to thy ſleeping Friends,</l>
                  <l>That could not watch one houre for love of thee,</l>
                  <l>Even thoſe three Friends, which on thy Grace depends,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhut thoſe Eies that ſhould their Maker ſee;</l>
                  <l>What colour, what excuſe, or what amends</l>
                  <l>From thy Diſpleaſure now can ſet them free?</l>
                  <l>Yet thy pure Pietie bids them Watch and Pray,</l>
                  <l>Leſt in Temptation they be led away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Although the Spirit was willing to obay,</l>
                  <l>Yet what great weakeneſſe in the Fleſh was found!</l>
                  <l>They ſlept in Eaſe, whilſt thou in Paine didſt pray;</l>
                  <l>Loe, they in Sleepe, and thou in Sorow drown'd:</l>
                  <l>Yet Gods right Hand was vnto thee a ſtay,</l>
                  <l>When horror, griefe, and ſorow did abound:</l>
                  <l>His Angel did appeare from Heaven to thee,</l>
                  <l>To yeeld thee comfort in Extremitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But what could comfort then thy troubled Minde,</l>
                  <l>When Heaven and Earth were both againſt thee bent?</l>
                  <l>And thou no hope, no eaſe, no reſt could'ſt finde,</l>
                  <l>But muſt reſtore that Life, which was but lent;</l>
                  <l>Was ever Creature in the World ſo kinde,</l>
                  <l>But he that from Eternitie was ſent?</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie for many Worlds of Sinne,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe matchieſſe Torments did but then begin.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:30"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>If one Mans ſinne doth challenge Death and Hell,</l>
                  <l>With all the Torments that belong thereto:</l>
                  <l>If for one ſinne ſuch Plagues on <hi>David</hi> fell,</l>
                  <l>As grieved him, and did his Seed vndoe:</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Salomon,</hi> for that he did not well,</l>
                  <l>Falling from Grace, did looſe his Kingdome too:</l>
                  <l>Ten Tribes beeing taken from his wilfull Sonne,</l>
                  <l>And Sinne the Cauſe that they were all vndone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What could thy Innocency now expect,</l>
                  <l>When all the Sinnes that ever were committed,</l>
                  <l>Were laid to thee, whom no man could detect?</l>
                  <l>Yet farre thou wert of Man from beeing pittied,</l>
                  <l>The Iudge ſo iuſt could yeeld thee no reſpect,</l>
                  <l>Nor would one jot of penance be remitted;</l>
                  <l>But greater horror to thy Soule muſt riſe,</l>
                  <l>Than Heart can thinke, or any Wit deviſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now drawes the houre of thy affliction neere,</l>
                  <l>And vgly Death preſents himſelfe before thee;</l>
                  <l>Thou now muſt leaue thoſe Friends thou held'ſt ſo deere,</l>
                  <l>Yea thoſe Diſciples, who did moſt adore thee;</l>
                  <l>Yet in thy countenance doth no Wrath appeare,</l>
                  <l>Although betrayd to thoſe that did abhorre thee:</l>
                  <l>Thou did'ſt vouchſafe to viſit them againe,</l>
                  <l>Who had no apprehenſion of thy paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Their eyes were heavie, and their hearts aſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Nor knew they well what anſwere then to make thee;</l>
                  <l>Yet thou as Watchman, had'ſt a care to keepe</l>
                  <l>Thoſe few from ſinne, that ſhortly would forſake thee;</l>
                  <l>But now thou bidſt them henceforth Reſt and Sleepe,</l>
                  <l>Thy houre is come, and they at hand to take thee:</l>
                  <l>The Sonne of God to Sinners made a pray,</l>
                  <l>Oh hatefull houre! oh bleſt! oh curſed day!</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:31"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe here thy great Humility was found,</l>
                  <l>Beeing King of Heauen, and Monarch of the Earth,</l>
                  <l>Yet well content to haue thy Glory drownd,</l>
                  <l>By beeing counted of ſo meane a berth;</l>
                  <l>Grace, Loue, and Mercy did ſo much abound,</l>
                  <l>Thou entertaindſt the Croſſe, euen to the death:</l>
                  <l>And nam'dſt thy ſelfe, the ſonne of Man to be,</l>
                  <l>To purge our pride by thy Humilitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now thy friends whom thou didſt call to goe,</l>
                  <l>Heauy Spectators of thy hapleſſe caſe,</l>
                  <l>See thy Betrayer, whom too well they knowe,</l>
                  <l>One of the twelue, now object of diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>A trothleſſe traytor, and a mortall foe,</l>
                  <l>With fained kindneſſe ſeekes thee to imbrace;</l>
                  <l>And giues a kiſſe, whereby he may deceiue thee,</l>
                  <l>That in the hands of Sinners he might leaue thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now muſter forth with Swords, with Staues, with Bils,</l>
                  <l>High Prieſts and Scribes, and Elders of the Land,</l>
                  <l>Seeking by force to haue their wicked Wils,</l>
                  <l>Which thou didſt neuer purpoſe to withſtand;</l>
                  <l>Now thou mak'ſt haſte vnto the worſt of Ils,</l>
                  <l>And who they ſeeke, thou gently doeſt demand;</l>
                  <l>This didſt thou Lord, t'amaze theſe Fooles the more,</l>
                  <l>T'inquire of that, thou knew'ſt ſo well before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When loe theſe Monſters did not ſhame to tell,</l>
                  <l>His name they ſought, and found, yet could not know</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ieſus</hi> of Nazareth, at whoſe feet they fell,</l>
                  <l>When Heauenly Wiſdome did deſcend ſo lowe</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak to them: they knew they did not well,</l>
                  <l>Their great amazement made them backeward goe:</l>
                  <l>Nay, though he ſaid vnto them, I am he,</l>
                  <l>They could not know him, whom their eyes did ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:31"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>How blinde were they could not diſcerne the Light!</l>
                  <l>How dull! if not to vnderſtand the truth,</l>
                  <l>How weake! if meekeneſſe overcame their might;</l>
                  <l>How ſtony hearted, if not mov'd to ruth:</l>
                  <l>How void of Pitie, and how full of Spight,</l>
                  <l>Gainſt him that was the Lord of Light and Truth:</l>
                  <l>Here inſolent Boldneſſe checkt by Love and Grace,</l>
                  <l>Retires, and falls before our Makers face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For when he ſpake to this accurſed crew,</l>
                  <l>And mildely made them know that it was he:</l>
                  <l>Preſents himſelfe, that they might take a view;</l>
                  <l>And what they doubted they might cleerely ſee;</l>
                  <l>Nay more, to re-aſſure that it was true,</l>
                  <l>He ſaid: I ſay vnto you, I am hee.</l>
                  <l>If him they ſought, he's willing to obay,</l>
                  <l>Onely deſires the reſt might goe their way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus with a heart prepared to endure</l>
                  <l>The greateſt wrongs Impietie could deviſe,</l>
                  <l>He was content to ſtoope vnto their Lure,</l>
                  <l>Although his Greatneſſe might doe otherwiſe:</l>
                  <l>Here Grace was ſeiſed on with hands impure,</l>
                  <l>And Virtue now muſt be ſuppreſt by Vice,</l>
                  <l>Pure Innocencie made a prey to Sinne,</l>
                  <l>Thus did his Torments and our Ioyes beginne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here faire Obedience ſhined in his breaſt,</l>
                  <l>And did ſuppreſſe all feare of future paine;</l>
                  <l>Love was his Leader vnto this vnreſt,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt Righteouſneſſe doth carry vp his Traine;</l>
                  <l>Mercy made way to make vs highly bleſt,</l>
                  <l>When Patience beat downe Sorrow, Feare and Paine:</l>
                  <l>Iuſtice ſate looking with an angry brow,</l>
                  <l>On bleſſed miſery appeering now.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:32"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>More glorious than all the Conquerors</l>
                  <l>That euer liu'd within this Earthly round,</l>
                  <l>More powrefull than all Kings, or Gouernours</l>
                  <l>That euer yet within this World were found;</l>
                  <l>More valiant than the greateſt Souldiers</l>
                  <l>That euer fought, to haue their glory crown'd:</l>
                  <l>For which of them, that euer yet tooke breath,</l>
                  <l>Sought t'indure the doome of Heauen and Earth?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But our ſweet Sauiour whom theſe Iewes did name;</l>
                  <l>Yet could their learned Ignorance apprehend</l>
                  <l>No light of grace, to free themſelues from blame:</l>
                  <l>Zeale, Lawes, Religion, now they doe pretend</l>
                  <l>Againſt the truth, vntruths they ſeeke to frame:</l>
                  <l>Now al their powres, their wits, their ſtrengths, they bend</l>
                  <l>Againſt one ſiely, weake, vnarmed man,</l>
                  <l>Who no reſiſtance makes, though much he can,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To free himſelfe from theſe vnlearned men,</l>
                  <l>Who call'd him Sauiour in his bleſſed name;</l>
                  <l>Yet farre from knowing him their Sauiour then,</l>
                  <l>That came to ſaue both them and theirs from blame;</l>
                  <l>Though they retire and fall, they come agen</l>
                  <l>To make a ſurer purchaſe of their ſhame:</l>
                  <l>With lights and torches now they find the way,</l>
                  <l>To take the Shepheard whilſt the ſheep doe ſtray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why ſhould vnlawfull actions vſe the Light?</l>
                  <l>Inniquitie in Darkeneſſe ſeekes to dwell;</l>
                  <l>Sinne rides his circuit in the dead of Night,</l>
                  <l>Teaching all ſoules the ready waies to hell;</l>
                  <l>Sathan coms arm'd with all the powres of Spight,</l>
                  <l>Heartens his Champions, makes them rude and fell;</l>
                  <l>Like rau'ning wolues, to ſhed his guiltleſſe blood,</l>
                  <l>Who thought no harme, but di'd to doe them good.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:32"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here Falſhood beares the ſhew of formall Right,</l>
                  <l>Baſe Treacherie hath gote a guard of men;</l>
                  <l>Tyranny attends, with all his ſtrength and might,</l>
                  <l>To leade this ſiely Lamb to Lyons denne;</l>
                  <l>Yet he vnmoou'd in this moſt wretched plight,</l>
                  <l>Goes on to meete them, knowes the houre, and when:</l>
                  <l>The powre of darkeneſſe muſt expreſſe Gods ire,</l>
                  <l>Therefore to ſaue theſe few was his deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe few that wait on Pouerty and Shame,</l>
                  <l>And offer to be ſharers in his Ils;</l>
                  <l>Theſe few that will be ſpreaders of his Fame,</l>
                  <l>He will not leaue to Tyrants wicked wils;</l>
                  <l>But ſtill deſires to free them from all blame,</l>
                  <l>Yet Feare goes forward, Anger Patience kils:</l>
                  <l>A Saint is mooued to reuenge a wrong,</l>
                  <l>And Mildneſſe doth what doth to Wrath belong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For <hi>Peter</hi> grieu'd at what might then befall,</l>
                  <l>Yet knew not what to doe, nor what to thinke,</l>
                  <l>Thought ſomething muſt be done; now, if at all,</l>
                  <l>To free his Maſter, that he might not drinke</l>
                  <l>This poys'ned draught, farre bitterer than gall,</l>
                  <l>For now he ſees him at the very brinke</l>
                  <l>Of grieſly Death, who gins to ſhew his face,</l>
                  <l>Clad in all colours of a deepe diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And now thoſe hands, that neuer vs'd to fight,</l>
                  <l>Or drawe a weapon in his owne defence,</l>
                  <l>Too forward is, to doe his Maſter right,</l>
                  <l>Since of his wrongs, hee feeles ſo true a ſence:</l>
                  <l>But ah poore <hi>Peter!</hi> now thou wanteſt might,</l>
                  <l>And hee's reſolu'd, with them he will goe hence:</l>
                  <l>To draw thy ſword in ſuch a helpeleſſe cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Offends thy Lord, and is againſt the Lawes.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:33"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>So much he hates Revenge, ſo farre from Hate,</l>
                  <l>That he vouchſafes to heale, whom thou doſt wound;</l>
                  <l>His paths are Peace, with none he holdes Debate,</l>
                  <l>His Patience ſtands vpon ſo ſure a ground,</l>
                  <l>To counſell thee, although it comes too late:</l>
                  <l>Nay, to his foes, his mercies ſo abound,</l>
                  <l>That he in pitty doth thy will reſtraine,</l>
                  <l>And heales the hurt, and takes away the paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For willingly he will endure this wrong,</l>
                  <l>Although his pray'rs might have obtain'd ſuch grace,</l>
                  <l>As to diſſolve their plots though ne'r ſo ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>And bring theſe wicked Actors in worſe caſe</l>
                  <l>Than <hi>Aegypts</hi> King on whom Gods plagues did throng,</l>
                  <l>But that foregoing Scriptures muſt take place:</l>
                  <l>If God by prayers had an army ſent</l>
                  <l>Of powrefull Angels, who could them prevent?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet mightie IESVS meekely ask'd, Why they</l>
                  <l>With Swords and Staves doe come as to a Thiefe?</l>
                  <l>Hee teaching in the Temple day by day</l>
                  <l>None did offend, or give him cauſe of griefe.</l>
                  <l>Now all are forward, glad is he that may</l>
                  <l>Give moſt offence, and yeeld him leaſt reliefe:</l>
                  <l>His hatefull foes are ready now to take him,</l>
                  <l>And all his deere Diſciples do forſake him.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe deare Diſciples that he moſt did love,</l>
                  <l>And were attendant at his becke and call,</l>
                  <l>When triall of affliction came to prove,</l>
                  <l>They firſt left him, who now muſt leave them all:</l>
                  <l>For they were earth, and he came from above,</l>
                  <l>Which made them apt to flie, and fit to fall:</l>
                  <l>Though they proteſt they never will forſake him,</l>
                  <l>They do like men, when dangers overtake them.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:33"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And he alone is bound to looſe vs all,</l>
                  <l>Whom with vnhallowed hands they led along,</l>
                  <l>To wicked <hi>Caiphas</hi> in the Iudgement Hall,</l>
                  <l>Who ſtudies onely how to doe him wrong;</l>
                  <l>High Prieſts and Elders, People great and ſmall,</l>
                  <l>With all reprochfull words about him throng:</l>
                  <l>Falſe Witneſſes are now call'd in apace,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe trothleſſe tongues muſt make pale death imbrace</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The beauty of the World, Heauens chiefeſt Glory;</l>
                  <l>The mirrour of Martyrs, Crowne of holy Saints;</l>
                  <l>Loue of th'Almighty, bleſſed Angels ſtory;</l>
                  <l>Water of Life, which none that drinks it, faints;</l>
                  <l>Guide of the Iuſt, where all our Light we borrow;</l>
                  <l>Mercy of Mercies; Hearer of Complaints;</l>
                  <l>Triumpher ouer Death; Ranſomer of Sinne;</l>
                  <l>Falſly accuſed: now his paines begin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Their tongues doe ſerue him as a Paſſing bell,</l>
                  <l>For what they ſay is certainly beleeued;</l>
                  <l>So ſound a tale vnto the Iudge they tell,</l>
                  <l>That he of Life muſt ſhortly be bereaued;</l>
                  <l>Their ſhare of Heauen, they doe not care to ſell,</l>
                  <l>So his afflicted Heart be throughly grieued:</l>
                  <l>They tell his Words, though farre from his intent,</l>
                  <l>And what his Speeches were, not what he meant.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That he Gods holy Temple could deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>And in three daies could build it vp againe;</l>
                  <l>This ſeem'd to them a vaine and idle toy,</l>
                  <l>It would not ſinke into their ſinful braine:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſts</hi> bleſſed body, al true Chriſtians joy,</l>
                  <l>Should die, and in three dayes reuiue againe:</l>
                  <l>This did the Lord of Heauen and earth endure,</l>
                  <l>Vniuſtly to be charg'd by tongues impure.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:34"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And now they all doe giue attentiue eare,</l>
                  <l>To heare the anſwere, which he will not make;</l>
                  <l>The people wonder how he can forbeare,</l>
                  <l>And theſe great wrongs ſo patiently can take;</l>
                  <l>But yet he anſwers not, nor doth he care,</l>
                  <l>Much more he will endure for our ſake:</l>
                  <l>Nor can their wiſdoms any way diſcouer,</l>
                  <l>Who he ſhould be that proou'd ſo true a Louer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To entertaine the ſharpeſt pangs of death,</l>
                  <l>And fight a combate in the depth of hell,</l>
                  <l>For wretched Worldlings made of duſt and earth,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hard'ned hearts, with pride and mallice ſwell;</l>
                  <l>In midſt of bloody ſweat, and dying breath,</l>
                  <l>He had compaſſion on theſe tyrants fell:</l>
                  <l>And purchaſt them a place in Heau'n for euer,</l>
                  <l>When they his Soule and Body ſought to ſeuer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sinnes vgly miſts, ſo blinded had their eyes,</l>
                  <l>That at Noone dayes they could diſcerne no Light;</l>
                  <l>Theſe were thoſe fooles, that thought themſelues ſo wiſe,</l>
                  <l>The Iewiſh wolues, that did our Sauiour bite;</l>
                  <l>For now they vſe all meanes they can deuiſe,</l>
                  <l>To beate downe truth, and goe againſt all right:</l>
                  <l>Yea now they take Gods holy name in vaine,</l>
                  <l>To know the truth, which truth they doe prophane.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The chiefeſt Hel-hounds of this hatefull crew,</l>
                  <l>Roſe vp to aske what anſwere he could make,</l>
                  <l>Againſt thoſe falſe accuſers in his view;</l>
                  <l>That by his ſpeech, they might aduantage take:</l>
                  <l>He held his peace, yet knew they ſaid not true,</l>
                  <l>No anſwere would his holy wiſdome make,</l>
                  <l>Till he was charged in his glorious name,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pleaſure twas he ſhould endure this ſhame.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:34"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then with ſo mild a Maieſtie he ſpake,</l>
                  <l>As they might eaſly know from whence he came,</l>
                  <l>His harmeleſſe tongue doth no exceptions take,</l>
                  <l>Nor Prieſts, nor People, meanes he now to blame;</l>
                  <l>But anſwers Folly, for true Wiſdomes ſake,</l>
                  <l>Beeing charged deeply by his powrefull name,</l>
                  <l>To tell if Chriſt the Sonne of God he be,</l>
                  <l>Who for our ſinnes muſt die, to ſet vs free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To thee O <hi>Caiphas</hi> doth he anſwere giue,</l>
                  <l>That thou haſt ſaid, what thou deſir'ſt to know,</l>
                  <l>And yet thy malice will not let him liue,</l>
                  <l>So much thou art vnto thy ſelfe a foe;</l>
                  <l>He ſpeaketh truth, but thou wilt not beleeue,</l>
                  <l>Nor canſt thou apprehend it to be ſo:</l>
                  <l>Though he expreſſe his Glory vnto thee,</l>
                  <l>Thy Owly eies are blind, and cannot ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou rend'ſt thy cloathes, in ſtead of thy falſe heart,</l>
                  <l>And on the guiltleſſe lai'ſt thy guilty crime;</l>
                  <l>For thou blaſphem'ſt, and he muſt feele the ſmart:</l>
                  <l>To ſentence death, thou think'ſt it now high time;</l>
                  <l>No witneſſe now thou need'ſt, for this fowle part,</l>
                  <l>Thou to the height of wickedneſſe canſt clime:</l>
                  <l>And giue occaſion to the ruder ſort,</l>
                  <l>To make afflictions, ſorrows, follies ſport.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now when the dawne of day gins to appeare,</l>
                  <l>And all your wicked counſels haue an end,</l>
                  <l>To end his Life, that holds you all ſo deere,</l>
                  <l>For to that purpoſe did your ſtudies bend;</l>
                  <l>Proud <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> muſt the matter heare,</l>
                  <l>To your vntroths his eares he now muſt lend:</l>
                  <l>Sweet <hi>Ieſus</hi> bound, to him you led away,</l>
                  <l>Of his moſt pretious blood to make yout pray.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:35"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which, when that wicked Caytife did perceiue,</l>
                  <l>By whoſe lewd meanes he came to this diſtreſſe;</l>
                  <l>He brought the price of blood he did receiue,</l>
                  <l>Thinking thereby to make his fault ſeeme leſſe,</l>
                  <l>And with theſe Prieſts and Elders did it leaue,</l>
                  <l>Confeſt his fault, wherein he did tranſgreſſe:</l>
                  <l>But when he ſaw Repentance vnreſpected,</l>
                  <l>He hang'd himſelfe; of God and Man reiected.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By this Example, what can be expected</l>
                  <l>From wicked Man, which on the Earth doth liue?</l>
                  <l>But faithleſſe dealing, feare of God neglected;</l>
                  <l>Who for their priuate gaine cares not to ſell</l>
                  <l>The Innocent Blood of Gods moſt deere elected,</l>
                  <l>As did that caytife wretch, now damn'd in Hell:</l>
                  <l>If in Chriſts Schoole, he tooke ſo great a fall,</l>
                  <l>What will they doe, that come not there at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> is to judge the Cauſe</l>
                  <l>Of faultleſſe <hi>Ieſus,</hi> who before him ſtands;</l>
                  <l>Who neither hath offended Prince, nor Lawes,</l>
                  <l>Although he now be brought in woefull bands:</l>
                  <l>O noble Gouernour, make thou yet a pauſe,</l>
                  <l>Doe not in innocent blood imbrue thy hands;</l>
                  <l>But heare the words of thy moſt worthy wife,</l>
                  <l>Who ſends to thee, to beg her Sauiours life.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let barb'rous crueltie farre depart from thee,</l>
                  <l>And in true Iuſtice take afflictions part;</l>
                  <l>Open thine eies, that thou the truth mai'ſt ſee,</l>
                  <l>Doe not the thing that goes againſt thy heart,</l>
                  <l>Condemne not him that muſt thy Sauiour be;</l>
                  <l>But view his holy Life, his good deſert.</l>
                  <l>Let not vs Women glory in Mens fall,</l>
                  <l>Who had power giuen to ouer-rule vs all.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Eues Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:35"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Till now your indiſcretion ſets vs free,</l>
                  <l>And makes our former fault much leſſe appeare;</l>
                  <l>Our Mother <hi>Eue,</hi> who taſted of the Tree,</l>
                  <l>Giuing to <hi>Adam</hi> what ſhee held moſt deare,</l>
                  <l>Was ſimply good, and had no powre to ſee,</l>
                  <l>The after-comming harine did not appeare:</l>
                  <l>The ſubtile Serpent that our Sex betraide,</l>
                  <l>Before our fall ſo ſure a plot had laide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That vndiſcerning Ignorance perceau'd</l>
                  <l>No guile, or craft that was by him intended;</l>
                  <l>For had ſhe knowne, of what we were bereau'd,</l>
                  <l>To his requeſt ſhe had not condiſcended.</l>
                  <l>But ſhe (poore ſoule) by cunning was deceau'd,</l>
                  <l>No hurt therein her harmeleſſe Heart intended:</l>
                  <l>For ſhe alleadg'd Gods word, which he denies,</l>
                  <l>That they ſhould die, but euen as Gods, be wiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſurely <hi>Adam</hi> can not be excuſde,</l>
                  <l>Her fault though great, yet hee was moſt too blame;</l>
                  <l>What Weakneſſe offerd, Strength might haue refuſde,</l>
                  <l>Being Lord of all, the greater was his ſhame:</l>
                  <l>Although the Serpents craft had her abuſde,</l>
                  <l>Gods holy word ought all his actions frame,</l>
                  <l>For he was Lord and King of all the earth,</l>
                  <l>Before poore <hi>Eue</hi> had either life or breath.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who being fram'd by Gods eternall hand,</l>
                  <l>The perfect'ſt man that ever breath'd on earth;</l>
                  <l>And from Gods mouth receiu'd that ſtrait command,</l>
                  <l>The breach whereof he knew was preſent death:</l>
                  <l>Yea hauing powre to rule both Sea and Land,</l>
                  <l>Yet with one Apple wonne to looſe that breath</l>
                  <l>Which God had breathed in his beauteous face,</l>
                  <l>Bringing vs all in danger and diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:36"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And then to lay the fault on Patience backe,</l>
                  <l>That we (poore women) muſt endure it all;</l>
                  <l>We know right well he did diſcretion lacke,</l>
                  <l>Beeing not perſwaded thereunto at all;</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Eue</hi> did erre, it was for knowledge ſake,</l>
                  <l>The fruit beeing faire perſwaded him to fall:</l>
                  <l>No ſubtill Serpents falſhood did betray him,</l>
                  <l>If he would eate it, who had powre to ſtay him?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not <hi>Eue,</hi> whoſe fault was onely too much loue,</l>
                  <l>Which made her giue this preſent to her Deare,</l>
                  <l>That what ſhee taſted, he likewiſe might proue,</l>
                  <l>Whereby his knowledge might become more cleare;</l>
                  <l>He neuer ſought her weakeneſſe to reproue,</l>
                  <l>With thoſe ſharpe words, which he of God did heare:</l>
                  <l>Yet Men will boaſt of Knowledge, which he tooke</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Eues</hi> faire hand, as from a learned Booke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If any Euill did in her remaine,</l>
                  <l>Beeing made of him, he was the ground of all;</l>
                  <l>If one of many Worlds could lay a ſtaine</l>
                  <l>Vpon our Sexe, and worke ſo great a fall</l>
                  <l>To wretched Man, by Satans ſubtill traine;</l>
                  <l>What will ſo fowle a fault amongſt you all?</l>
                  <l>Her weakeneſſe did the Serpents words obay,</l>
                  <l>But you in malice Gods deare Sonne betray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whom, if vniuſtly you condemne to die,</l>
                  <l>Her ſinne was ſmall, to what you doe commit;</l>
                  <l>All mortall finnes that doe for vengeance crie,</l>
                  <l>Are not to be compared vnto it:</l>
                  <l>If many worlds would altogether trie,</l>
                  <l>By all their ſinnes the wrath of God to get;</l>
                  <l>This ſinne of yours, ſurmounts them all as farre</l>
                  <l>As doth the Sunne, another little ſtarre.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:36"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then let vs haue our Libertie againe,</l>
                  <l>And challendge to your ſelues no Sou'raigntie;</l>
                  <l>You came not in the world without our paine,</l>
                  <l>Make that a barre againſt your crueltie;</l>
                  <l>Your fault beeing greater, why ſhould you diſdaine</l>
                  <l>Our beeing your equals free from tyranny?</l>
                  <l>If one weake woman ſimply did offend,</l>
                  <l>This ſinne of yours, hath no excuſe, nor end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To which (poore ſoules) we neuer gaue conſent,</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe thy wife (O <hi>Pilate</hi>) ſpeakes for all;</l>
                  <l>Who did but dreame, and yet a meſſage ſent,</l>
                  <l>That thou ſhould'ſt haue nothing to doe at all</l>
                  <l>With that juſt man; which, if thy heart relent,</l>
                  <l>Why wilt thou be a reprobate with <hi>Saul?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſeeke the death of him that is ſo good,</l>
                  <l>For thy ſoules health to ſhed his deareſt blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yea, ſo thou mai'ſt theſe ſinful people pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Thou art content againſt all truth and right,</l>
                  <l>To ſeale this act, that may procure thine eaſe</l>
                  <l>With blood, and wrong, with tyrannie, and might;</l>
                  <l>The multitude thou ſeekeſt to appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>By baſe deiection of this heauenly Light:</l>
                  <l>Demanding which of theſe that thou ſhould'ſt looſe,</l>
                  <l>Whether the Thiefe, or Chriſt King of the Iewes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Baſe <hi>Barrabas</hi> the Thiefe, they all deſire,</l>
                  <l>And thou more baſe than he, perform'ſt their will;</l>
                  <l>Yet when thy thoughts backe to themſeluesretire,</l>
                  <l>Thou art vnwilling to commit this ill:</l>
                  <l>Oh that thou couldſt vnto ſuch grace aſpire,</l>
                  <l>That thy polluted lips might neuer kill</l>
                  <l>That Honour, which right Iudgement euer graceth,</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe ſhame, which all true worth defaceth.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:37"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Art thou a Iudge, and asketh what to do</l>
                  <l>With one, in whom no fault there can be found?</l>
                  <l>The death of Chriſt wilt thou conſent vnto,</l>
                  <l>Finding no cauſe, no reaſon, nor no ground?</l>
                  <l>Shall he be ſcourg'd, and crucified too?</l>
                  <l>And muſt his miſeries by thy meanes abound?</l>
                  <l>Yet not aſham'd to aske what he hath done,</l>
                  <l>When thine owne conſcience ſeeks this ſinne to ſhunne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Three times thou ask'ſt, What euill hath he done?</l>
                  <l>And ſaiſt, thou find'ſt in him no cauſe of death,</l>
                  <l>Yet wilt thou chaſten Gods beloued Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Although to thee no word of ill he ſaith:</l>
                  <l>For Wrath muſt end, what Malice hath begunne,</l>
                  <l>And thou muſt yield to ſtop his guiltleſſe breath.</l>
                  <l>This rude tumultuous rowt doth preſſe ſo ſore,</l>
                  <l>That thou condemneſt him thou ſhouldſt adore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet <hi>Pilate,</hi> this can yeeld thee no content,</l>
                  <l>To exerciſe thine owne authoritie,</l>
                  <l>But vnto <hi>Herod</hi> he muſt needes be ſent,</l>
                  <l>To reconcile thy ſelfe by tyrannie:</l>
                  <l>Was this the greateſt good in Iuſtice meant,</l>
                  <l>When thou perceiu'ſt no fault in him to be?</l>
                  <l>If thou muſt make thy peace by Virtues fall,</l>
                  <l>Much better 'twere not to be friends at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet neither thy ſterne browe, nor his great place,</l>
                  <l>Can draw an anſwer from the Holy One:</l>
                  <l>His falſe accuſers, nor his great diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Herods</hi> ſcoffes; to him they are all one:</l>
                  <l>He neither cares, nor feares his owne ill caſe,</l>
                  <l>Though being deſpis'd and mockt of euery one:</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Herods</hi> gladneſſe giues him little eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Neither his anger ſeekes he to appeaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:37"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet this is ſtrange, that baſe Impietie</l>
                  <l>Should yeeld thoſe robes of honour, which were due;</l>
                  <l>Pure white, to ſhew his great Integritie,</l>
                  <l>His innocency, that all the world might view;</l>
                  <l>Perfections height in loweſt penury,</l>
                  <l>Such glorious pouerty as they neuer knew:</l>
                  <l>Purple and Scarlet well might him beſeeme,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pretious blood muſt all the world redeeme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And that Imperiall Crowne of Thornes he wore,</l>
                  <l>Was much more pretious than the Diadem</l>
                  <l>Of any King that euer liu'd before,</l>
                  <l>Or ſince his time, their honour's but a dreame</l>
                  <l>To his eternall glory, beeing ſo poore,</l>
                  <l>To make a purchaſſe of that heauenly Realme;</l>
                  <l>Where God with all his Angels liues in peace,</l>
                  <l>No griefes, nor ſorrowes, but all joyes increaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe royall robes, which they in ſcorne did giue,</l>
                  <l>To make him odious to the common ſort,</l>
                  <l>Yeeld light of Grace to thoſe whoſe ſoules ſhall liue</l>
                  <l>Within the harbour of this heauenly port;</l>
                  <l>Much doe they joy, and much more doe they grieue,</l>
                  <l>His death, their life, ſhould make his foes ſuch ſport:</l>
                  <l>With ſharpeſt thornes to pricke his bleſſed face,</l>
                  <l>Our joyfull ſorrow, and his greater grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Three feares at once poſſeſſed <hi>Pilates</hi> heart;</l>
                  <l>The firſt, Chriſts innocencie, which ſo plaine appeares;</l>
                  <l>The next, That he which now muſt feele this ſinart,</l>
                  <l>Is Gods deare Sonne, for any thing he heares:</l>
                  <l>But that which proou'd the deepeſt wounding dart,</l>
                  <l>Is Peoples threat'nings, which he ſo much feares,</l>
                  <l>That he to <hi>Caeſar</hi> could not be a friend,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe he ſent ſweet IESVS to his end.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:38"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Pilate</hi> thou art proou'da painted wall,</l>
                  <l>A golden Sepulcher with rotten bones;</l>
                  <l>From right to wrong, from equitie to fall:</l>
                  <l>If none vpbraid thee, yet the very ſtones</l>
                  <l>Will riſe againſt thee, and in queſtion call</l>
                  <l>His blood, his teares, his ſighes, his bitter groanes:</l>
                  <l>All theſe will witneſſe at the latter day,</l>
                  <l>When water cannot waſh thy ſinne away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Canſt thou be innocent, that gainſt all right,</l>
                  <l>Wilt yeeld to what thy conſcience doth withſtand?</l>
                  <l>Beeing a man of knowledge, powre, and might,</l>
                  <l>To let the wicked carrie ſuch a hand,</l>
                  <l>Before thy face to blindfold Heau'ns bright light,</l>
                  <l>And thou to yeeld to what they did demand?</l>
                  <l>Waſhing thy hands, thy conſcience cannot cleare,</l>
                  <l>But to all worlds this ſtaine muſt needs appeare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For loe, the Guiltie doth accuſe the Iuſt,</l>
                  <l>And faultie Iudge condemnes the Innocent;</l>
                  <l>And wilfull Iewes to exerciſe their luſt,</l>
                  <l>With whips and taunts againſt their Lord are bent;</l>
                  <l>He baſely vs'd, blaſphemed, ſcorn'd, and curſt,</l>
                  <l>Our heauenly King to death for vs they ſent:</l>
                  <l>Reproches, ſlanders, ſpittings in his face,</l>
                  <l>Spight doing all her worſt in his diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrist going <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> death.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ And now this long expected houre drawes neere,</l>
                  <l>When bleſſed Saints with Angels doe condole;</l>
                  <l>His holy march, ſoft pace, and heauy cheere,</l>
                  <l>In humble ſort to yeeld his glorious ſoule,</l>
                  <l>By his deſerts the fowleſt ſinnes to cleare;</l>
                  <l>And in th'eternall booke of heauen to enroule</l>
                  <l>A ſatisfaction till the generall doome,</l>
                  <l>Of all ſinnes paſt, and all that are to come.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:38"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>They that had ſeene this pitifull Proceſſion,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Pilates</hi> Palace to Mount Caluarie,</l>
                  <l>Might thinke he anſwer'd for ſome great tranſgreſſion,</l>
                  <l>Beeing in ſuch odious ſort condemn'd to die;</l>
                  <l>He plainely ſhewed that his owne profeſſion</l>
                  <l>Was virtue, patience, grace, loue, piety;</l>
                  <l>And how by ſuffering he could conquer more</l>
                  <l>Than all the Kings that euer liu'd before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Firſt went the Crier with open mouth proclayming</l>
                  <l>The heauy ſentence of Iniquitie,</l>
                  <l>The Hangman next, by his baſe office clayming</l>
                  <l>His right in Hell, where ſinners neuer die,</l>
                  <l>Carrying the nayles, the people ſtill blaſpheming</l>
                  <l>Their maker, vſing all impiety;</l>
                  <l>The Thieues attending him on either ſide,</l>
                  <l>¶ The Serjeants watching, while the women cri'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The teares of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thrice happy women that obtaind ſuch grace</l>
                  <l>From him whoſe worth the world could not containe;</l>
                  <l>Immediately to turne about his face,</l>
                  <l>As not remembring his great griefe and paine,</l>
                  <l>To comfort you, whoſe teares powr'd forth apace</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Flora's</hi> bankes, like ſhewers of Aprils raine:</l>
                  <l>Your cries inforced mercie, grace, and loue</l>
                  <l>From him, whom greateſt Princes could not mooue</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To ſpeake on word, nor once to lift his eyes</l>
                  <l>Vnto proud <hi>Pilate,</hi> no nor <hi>Herod,</hi> king,</l>
                  <l>By all the Queſtions that they could deuiſe,</l>
                  <l>Could make him anſwere to no manner of thing;</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe poore women, by their pitious cries</l>
                  <l>Did mooue their Lord, their Louer, and their King,</l>
                  <l>To take compaſſion turne about, and ſpeake</l>
                  <l>To them whoſe hearts were ready now to breake.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:39"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt bleſſed daughters of Ieruſalem,</l>
                  <l>Who found ſuch fauour in your Sauiors ſight,</l>
                  <l>To turne his face when you did pitie him;</l>
                  <l>Your tearefull eyes, beheld his eies more bright;</l>
                  <l>Your Faith and Loue vnto ſuch grace did clime,</l>
                  <l>To haue reflection from this Heau'nly Light:</l>
                  <l>Your Eagles eyes did gaze againſt this Sunne,</l>
                  <l>Your hearts did thinke, he dead, the world were done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When ſpightfull men with torments did oppreſſe</l>
                  <l>Th'afflicted body of this innocent Doue,</l>
                  <l>Poore women ſeeing how much they did tranſgreſſe,</l>
                  <l>By teares, by ſighes, by cries intreat, nay proue,</l>
                  <l>What may be done among the thickeſt preſſe,</l>
                  <l>They labour ſtill theſe tyrants hearts to moue;</l>
                  <l>In pitie and compaſſion to forbeare</l>
                  <l>Their whipping, ſpurning, tearing of his haire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But all in vaine, their malice hath no end,</l>
                  <l>Their hearts more hard than ſlint, or marble ſtone;</l>
                  <l>Now to his griefe, his greatneſſe they attend,</l>
                  <l>When he (God knowes) had rather be alone;</l>
                  <l>They are his guard, yet ſeeke all meanes to offend:</l>
                  <l>Well may he grieue, well may he ſigh and groane,</l>
                  <l>Vnder the burthen of a heauy croſſe,</l>
                  <l>He faintly goes to make their gaine his loſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſorrow of the virgin <hi>Marie.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ His woefull Mother wayting on her Sonne,</l>
                  <l>All comfortleſſe in depth of ſorow drowned;</l>
                  <l>Her griefes extreame, although but new begun,</l>
                  <l>To ſee his bleeding body oft ſhee ſwouned;</l>
                  <l>How could ſhee chooſe but thinke her ſelfe vndone,</l>
                  <l>He dying, with whoſe glory ſhee was crowned?</l>
                  <l>None euer loſt ſo great a loſſe as ſhee,</l>
                  <l>Beeing Sonne, and Father of Eternitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:39"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her teares did waſh away his pretious blood,</l>
                  <l>That ſinners might not tread it vnder feet</l>
                  <l>To worſhip him, and that it did her good</l>
                  <l>Vpon her knees, although in open ſtreet,</l>
                  <l>Knowing he was the Ieſſie floure and bud,</l>
                  <l>That muſt be gath'red when it ſmell'd moſt ſweet:</l>
                  <l>Her Sonne, her Husband, Father, Saviour, King,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe death killd Death, and tooke away his ſting.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt bleſſed Virgin, in whoſe faultleſſe fruit,</l>
                  <l>All Nations of the earth muſt needes reioyce,</l>
                  <l>No Creature having ſence though ne'r ſo brute,</l>
                  <l>But ioyes and trembles when they heare his voyce;</l>
                  <l>His wiſedome ſtrikes the wiſeſt perſons mute,</l>
                  <l>Faire choſen veſſell, happy in his choyce:</l>
                  <l>Deere Mother of our Lord, whoſe reuerend name,</l>
                  <l>All people Bleſſed call, and ſpread thy fame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For the Almightie magnified thee,</l>
                  <l>And looked downe vpon thy meane eſtate;</l>
                  <l>Thy lowly mind, and vnſtain'd Chaſtitie,</l>
                  <l>Did pleade for Loue at great <hi>Iehouaes</hi> gate,</l>
                  <l>Who ſending ſwift-wing'd <hi>Gabriel</hi> vnto thee,</l>
                  <l>His holy will and pleaſure to relate;</l>
                  <l>To thee moſt beauteous Queene of Woman-kind,</l>
                  <l>The Angell did vnfold his Makers mind.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ He thus beganne, Haile <hi>Mary</hi> full of grace,</l>
                  <l>Thou freely art beloued of the Lord,</l>
                  <l>He is with thee, behold thy happy caſe;</l>
                  <l>What endleſſe comfort did theſe words afford</l>
                  <l>To thee that ſaw'ſt an Angell in the place</l>
                  <l>Proclaime thy Virtues worth, and to record</l>
                  <l>Thee bleſſed among women: that thy praiſe</l>
                  <l>Should laſt ſo many worlds beyond thy daies.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:40"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe, this high meſſage to thy troubled ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>He doth deliuer in the plaineſt ſence;</l>
                  <l>Sayes, Thou ſhouldſt beare a Sonne that ſhal inherit</l>
                  <l>His Father <hi>Dauids</hi> throne, free from offence,</l>
                  <l>Call's him that Holy thing, by whoſe pure merit</l>
                  <l>We muſt be ſau'd, tels what he is, of whence;</l>
                  <l>His worth, his greatneſſe, what his name muſt be,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhould be call'd the Sonne of the moſt High.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He cheeres thy troubled ſoule, bids thee not feare;</l>
                  <l>When thy pure thoughts could hardly apprehend</l>
                  <l>This ſalutation, when he did appeare;</l>
                  <l>Nor couldſt thou judge, whereto thoſe words did tend;</l>
                  <l>His pure aſpect did mooue thy modeſt cheere</l>
                  <l>To muſe, yet joy that God vouchſaf'd to ſend</l>
                  <l>His glorious Angel; who did thee aſſure</l>
                  <l>To beare a child, although a Virgin pure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay more, thy Sonne ſhould Rule and Raigne for euer;</l>
                  <l>Yea, of his Kingdom there ſhould be no end;</l>
                  <l>Ouer the houſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> Heauens great Giuer</l>
                  <l>Would giue him powre, and to that end did ſend</l>
                  <l>His faithfull ſeruant <hi>Gabriel</hi> to deliuer</l>
                  <l>To thy chaſt eares no word that might offend:</l>
                  <l>But that this bleſſed Infant borne of thee,</l>
                  <l>Thy Sonne, The onely Sonne of God ſhould be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When on the knees of thy ſubmiſſiue heart</l>
                  <l>Thou humbly didſt demand, How that ſhould be?</l>
                  <l>Thy virgin thoughts did thinke, none could impart</l>
                  <l>This great good hap, and bleſſing vnto thee;</l>
                  <l>Farre from deſire of any man thou art,</l>
                  <l>Knowing not one, thou art from all men free:</l>
                  <l>When he, to anſwere this thy chaſte deſire,</l>
                  <l>Giues thee more cauſe to wonder and admire.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:40"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>That thou a bleſſed Virgin ſhoulſt remaine,</l>
                  <l>Yea that the holy Ghoſt ſhould come on thee</l>
                  <l>A maiden Mother, ſubiect to no paine,</l>
                  <l>For higheſt powre ſhould ouerſhadow thee:</l>
                  <l>Could thy faire eyes from teares of joy refraine,</l>
                  <l>When God look'd downe vpon thy poore degree?</l>
                  <l>Making thee Seruant, Mother, Wife, and Nurſe</l>
                  <l>To Heauens bright King, that freed vs from the curſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus beeing crown'd with glory from aboue,</l>
                  <l>Grace and Perfection reſting in thy breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Thy humble anſwer doth approoue thy Loue,</l>
                  <l>And all theſe ſayings in thy heart doe reſt:</l>
                  <l>Thy Child a Lambe, and thou a Turtle doue,</l>
                  <l>Aboue all other women highly bleſt;</l>
                  <l>To find ſuch fauour in his glorious ſight,</l>
                  <l>In whom thy heart and ſoule doe moſt delight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What wonder in the world more ſtrange could ſeeme,</l>
                  <l>Than that a Virgin could conceiue and beare</l>
                  <l>Within her wombe a Sonne, That ſhould redeeme</l>
                  <l>All Nations on the earth, and ſhould repaire</l>
                  <l>Our old decaies: who in ſuch high eſteeme,</l>
                  <l>Should prize all mortals, liuing in his feare;</l>
                  <l>As not to ſhun Death, Pouertie, and Shame,</l>
                  <l>To ſaue their ſoules, and ſpread his glorious Name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And partly to fulfil his Fathers pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe powrefull hand allowes it not for ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>If he vouchſafe the riches of his treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Pure Righteouſneſſe to take ſuch il exchange;</l>
                  <l>On all Iniquitie to make a ſeiſure,</l>
                  <l>Giuing his ſnow-white Weed for ours in change;</l>
                  <l>Our mortall garment in a skarlet Die,</l>
                  <l>Too baſe a roabe for Immortalitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:41"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt happy news, that euer yet was brought,</l>
                  <l>When Pouerty and Riches met together,</l>
                  <l>The wealth of Heauen, in our fraile clothing wrought</l>
                  <l>Saluation by his happy comming hither:</l>
                  <l>Mighty Meſſias, who ſo deerely bought</l>
                  <l>Vs Slaues to finne, farre lighter than a feather:</l>
                  <l>Toſs'd to and fro with euery wicked wind,</l>
                  <l>The world, the fleſh, or Deuill giues to blind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who on his ſhoulders our blacke ſinnes doth beare</l>
                  <l>To that moſt bleſſed, yet accurſed Croſſe;</l>
                  <l>Where faſtning them, he rids vs of our feare,</l>
                  <l>Yea for our gaine he is content with loſſe,</l>
                  <l>Our ragged clothing ſcornes he not to weare,</l>
                  <l>Though foule, rent, torne, diſgracefull, rough and groſſe,</l>
                  <l>Spunne by that monſter Sinne, and weav'd by Shame,</l>
                  <l>Which grace it ſelfe, diſgrac'd with impure blame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How canſt thou chooſe (faire Virgin) then but mourne,</l>
                  <l>When this ſweet of-ſpring of thy body dies,</l>
                  <l>When thy faire eies beholds his bodie torne,</l>
                  <l>The peoples ſury, heares the womens cries;</l>
                  <l>His holy name prophan'd, He made a ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>Abuſde with all their hatefull ſlaunderous lies:</l>
                  <l>Bleeding and fainting in ſuch wondrous ſort,</l>
                  <l>As ſcarce his feeble limbes can him ſupport.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Cyrene</hi> paſſeth them by,</l>
                  <l>Whom they compell ſweet IESVS Croſſe to beare</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Golgatha,</hi> there doe they meane to trie</l>
                  <l>All cruell meanes to worke in him diſpaire:</l>
                  <l>That odious place, where dead mens skulls did lie,</l>
                  <l>There muſt our Lord for preſent death prepare:</l>
                  <l>His ſacred blood muſt grace that loathſome field,</l>
                  <l>To purge more filth, than that foule place could yield.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Christs death.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:41"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ For now arriu'd vnto this hatefull place,</l>
                  <l>In which his Croſſe erected needes muſt bee,</l>
                  <l>Falſe hearts, and willing hands come on apace,</l>
                  <l>All preſt to ill, and all deſire to ſee:</l>
                  <l>Graceleſſe themſelues, ſtill ſeeking to diſgrace;</l>
                  <l>Bidding him, If the Sonne of God he bee,</l>
                  <l>To ſaue himſelfe, if he could others ſaue,</l>
                  <l>With all th'opprobrious words that might depraue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His harmeleſſe hands vnto the Croſſe they nailde,</l>
                  <l>And feet that neuer trode in ſinners trace,</l>
                  <l>Betweene two theeues, vnpitied, vnbewailde,</l>
                  <l>Saue of ſome few poſſeſſors of his grace,</l>
                  <l>With ſharpeſt pangs and terrors thus appailde,</l>
                  <l>Sterne Death makes way, that Life might giue him place:</l>
                  <l>His eyes with teares, his body full of wounds,</l>
                  <l>Death laſt of paines his ſorrows all confounds.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His joynts diſ-joynted, and his legges hang downe,</l>
                  <l>His alablaſter breaſt, his bloody ſide,</l>
                  <l>His members torne, and on his head a Crowne</l>
                  <l>Of ſharpeſt Thorns, to ſatisfie for pride:</l>
                  <l>Anguiſh and Paine doe all his Sences drowne,</l>
                  <l>While they his holy garments do diuide:</l>
                  <l>His bowells drie, his heart full fraught with griefe,</l>
                  <l>Crying to him that yeelds him no reliefe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To my La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ This with the eie of Faith thou maiſt behold,</l>
                  <l>Deere Spouſe of Chriſt, and more than I can write;</l>
                  <l>And here both Griefe and Ioy thou maiſt vnfold,</l>
                  <l>To view thy Loue in this moſt heauy plight,</l>
                  <l>Bowing his head, his bloodleſſe body cold;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe eies waxe dimme that gaue vs all our light,</l>
                  <l>His count'nance pale, yet ſtill continues ſweet,</l>
                  <l>His bleſſed blood watring his pierced feet.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:42"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>O glorious miracle without compare!</l>
                  <l>Laſt, but not leaſt which was by him effected;</l>
                  <l>Vniting death, life, miſery, joy and care,</l>
                  <l>By his ſharpe paſſion in his deere elected:</l>
                  <l>Who doth the Badges of like Liueries weare,</l>
                  <l>Shall find how deere they are of him reſpected.</l>
                  <l>No joy, griefe, paine, life, death, was like to his,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe infinite dolours wrought eternall bliſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e terror of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> creatures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>riſt died.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ What creature on the earth did then remaine,</l>
                  <l>On whom the horror of this ſhamefull deed</l>
                  <l>Did not inflict ſome violent touch, or ſtraine,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the Lord of all the world to bleed?</l>
                  <l>His dying breath did rend huge rockes in twaine,</l>
                  <l>The heauens betooke them to their mourning weed:</l>
                  <l>The Sunne grew darke, and ſcorn'd to giue them light,</l>
                  <l>Who durſt ecclipſe a glory farre more bright.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Moone and Starres did hide themſelues for ſhame,</l>
                  <l>The earth did rremble in her loyall feare,</l>
                  <l>The Temple vaile did rent to ſpread his fame,</l>
                  <l>The Monuments did open euery where;</l>
                  <l>Dead Saints did riſe forth of their graues, and came</l>
                  <l>To diuers people that remained there</l>
                  <l>Within that holy City; whoſe offence,</l>
                  <l>Did put their Maker to this large expence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Things reaſonable, and reaſonleſſe poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>The terrible impreſſion of this fact;</l>
                  <l>For his oppreſſion made them all oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>When with his blood he ſeal'd ſo faire an act,</l>
                  <l>In reſtleſſe miſerie to procure our reſt;</l>
                  <l>His glorious deedes that dreadfull priſon ſackt:</l>
                  <l>When Death, Hell, Diuells, vſing all their powre,</l>
                  <l>Were ouercome in that moſt bleſſed houre.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:42"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Being dead, he killed Death, and did ſuruiue</l>
                  <l>That prowd inſulting Tyrant: in whoſe place</l>
                  <l>He ſends bright Immortalitie to reuiue</l>
                  <l>Thoſe whom his yron armes did long embrace;</l>
                  <l>Who from their loathſome graues brings them aliue</l>
                  <l>In glory to behold their Sauiours face:</l>
                  <l>Who tooke the keys of all Deaths powre away,</l>
                  <l>Opening to thoſe that would his name obay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O wonder, more than man can comprehend,</l>
                  <l>Our Ioy and Griefe both at one inſtant fram'd,</l>
                  <l>Compounded: Contrarieties contend</l>
                  <l>Each to exceed, yet neither to be blam'd.</l>
                  <l>Our Griefe to ſee our Sauiours wretched end,</l>
                  <l>Our Ioy to know both Death and Hell he tam'd:</l>
                  <l>That we may ſay, O Death, where is thy ſting?</l>
                  <l>Hell, yeeld thy victory to thy conq'ring King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Can ſtony hearts refraine from ſhedding teares,</l>
                  <l>To view the life and death of this ſweet Saint?</l>
                  <l>His auſtere courſe in yong and tender yeares,</l>
                  <l>When great indurements could not make him faint:</l>
                  <l>His wants, his paines, his torments, and his feares,</l>
                  <l>All which he vndertooke without conſtraint,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew that infinite Goodneſſe muſt reſtore,</l>
                  <l>What infinite Iuſtice looked for, and more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, had he beene but of a meane degree,</l>
                  <l>His ſuffrings had beene ſmall to what they were;</l>
                  <l>Meane minds will ſhew of what meane mouldes they bee;</l>
                  <l>Small griefes ſeeme great, yet Vſe doth make them beare:</l>
                  <l>But ah! tis hard to ſtirre a ſturdy tree;</l>
                  <l>Great dangers hardly puts great minds in feare:</l>
                  <l>They will conceale their griefes which mightie grow</l>
                  <l>In their ſtout hearts vntill they ouerflow.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:43"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>If then an earthly Prince may ill endure</l>
                  <l>The leaſt of thoſe afflictions which he bare,</l>
                  <l>How could this all-commaunding King procure</l>
                  <l>Such grieuous torments with his mind to ſquare,</l>
                  <l>Legions of Angells being at his Lure?</l>
                  <l>He might haue liu'd in pleaſure without care:</l>
                  <l>None can conceiue the bitter paines he felt,</l>
                  <l>When God and man muſt ſuffer without guilt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Take all the Suffrings Thoughts can thinke vpon,</l>
                  <l>In eu'ry man that this huge world hath bred;</l>
                  <l>Let all thoſe Paines and Suffrings meet in one,</l>
                  <l>Yet are they not a Mite to that he did</l>
                  <l>Endure for vs: Oh let vs thinke thereon,</l>
                  <l>That God ſhould haue his pretious blood ſo ſhed:</l>
                  <l>His Greatneſſe clothed in our fraile attire,</l>
                  <l>And pay ſo deare a ranſome for the hire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe, here was glorie, miſerie, life and death,</l>
                  <l>An vnion of contraries did accord;</l>
                  <l>Gladneſſe and ſadneſſe here had one berth,</l>
                  <l>This wonder wrought the Paſſion of our Lord,</l>
                  <l>He ſuffring for all the ſinnes of all th'earth,</l>
                  <l>No ſatisfaction could the world afford:</l>
                  <l>But this rich Iewell, which from God was ſent,</l>
                  <l>To call all thoſe that would in time repent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which I preſent (deare Lady) to your view,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Croſſe depriu'd of life or breath,</l>
                  <l>To judge if euer Louer were ſo true,</l>
                  <l>To yeeld himſelfe vnto ſuch ſhamefull death:</l>
                  <l>Now bleſſed <hi>Ioſeph</hi> doth both beg and ſue,</l>
                  <l>To haue his body who poſſeſt his faith,</l>
                  <l>And thinkes, if he this ſmall requeſt obtaines,</l>
                  <l>He wins more wealth than in the world remaines.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:43"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus honourable <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>Of what his heart and ſoule ſo much deſired,</l>
                  <l>And now he goes to giue that body reſt,</l>
                  <l>That all his life, with griefes and paines was tired;</l>
                  <l>He finds a Tombe, a Tombe moſt rarely bleſt,</l>
                  <l>In which was neuer creature yet interred;</l>
                  <l>There this moſt pretious body he incloſes,</l>
                  <l>Imbalmd and deckt with Lillies and with Roſes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe here the Beautie of Heau'n and Earth is laid,</l>
                  <l>The pureſt coulers vnderneath the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>But in this place he cannot long be ſtaid,</l>
                  <l>Glory muſt end what horror hath begun;</l>
                  <l>For he the furie of the Heauens obay'd,</l>
                  <l>And now he muſt poſſeſſe what he hath wonne:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Maries</hi> doe with pretious balmes attend,</l>
                  <l>But beeing come, they find it to no end.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Christs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ For he is rize from Death t'Eternall Life,</l>
                  <l>And now thoſe pretious oyntments he deſires</l>
                  <l>Are brought vnto him, by his faithfull Wife</l>
                  <l>The holy Church; who in thoſe rich attires,</l>
                  <l>Of Patience, Loue, Long ſuffring, Voide of ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Humbly preſents thoſe oyntments he requires:</l>
                  <l>The oyles of Mercie, Charitie, and Faith,</l>
                  <l>Shee onely giues that which no other hath.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A briefe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of his beautie vpon the Canticles.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Theſe pretious balmes doe heale his grieuous wounds,</l>
                  <l>And water of Compunction waſheth cleane</l>
                  <l>The ſoares of ſinnes, which in our Soules abounds;</l>
                  <l>So faire it heales, no skarre is euer ſeene;</l>
                  <l>Yet all the glory vnto Chriſt redounds,</l>
                  <l>His pretious blood is that which muſt redeeme;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe well may make vs louely in his ſight,</l>
                  <l>But cannot ſaue without his powrefull might.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:44"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is that Bridegroome that appeares ſo faire,</l>
                  <l>So ſweet, ſo louely in his Spouſes ſight,</l>
                  <l>That vnto Snowe we may his face compare,</l>
                  <l>His cheekes like skarlet, and his eyes ſo bright</l>
                  <l>As pureſt Doues that in the riuers are,</l>
                  <l>Waſhed with milke, to giue the more delight;</l>
                  <l>His head is likened to the fineſt gold,</l>
                  <l>His curled lockes ſo beauteous to behold;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Blacke as a Raven in her blackeſt hew;</l>
                  <l>His lips like skarlet threeds, yet much more ſweet</l>
                  <l>Than is the ſweeteſt hony dropping dew,</l>
                  <l>Or hony combes, where all the Bees doe meet;</l>
                  <l>Yea, he is conſtant, and his words are true,</l>
                  <l>His cheekes are beds of ſpices, flowers ſweet;</l>
                  <l>His lips like Lillies, dropping downe pure mirrhe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe loue, before all worlds we doe preferre.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To my Lady of Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Ah! giue me leaue (good Lady) now to leaue</l>
                  <l>This taske of Beauty which I tooke in hand,</l>
                  <l>I cannot wade ſo deepe, I may deceaue</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe, before I can attaine the land;</l>
                  <l>Therefore (good Madame) in your heart I leaue</l>
                  <l>His perfect picture, where it ſtill ſhall ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Deepely engraued in that holy ſhrine,</l>
                  <l>Enuironed with Loue and Thoughts diuine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There may you ſee him as a God in glory,</l>
                  <l>And as a man in miſerable caſe;</l>
                  <l>There may you reade his true and perfect ſtorie,</l>
                  <l>His bleeding body there you may embrace,</l>
                  <l>And kiſſe his dying cheekes with teares of ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>With ioyfull griefe, you may intreat for grace;</l>
                  <l>And all your prayers, and your almes-deeds</l>
                  <l>May bring to ſtop his cruell wounds that bleeds.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:44"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oft times hath he made triall of your loue,</l>
                  <l>And in your Faith hath tooke no ſmall delight,</l>
                  <l>By Croſſes and Afflictions he doth proue,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill your heart remaineth firme and right;</l>
                  <l>Your loue ſo ſtrong, as nothing can remoue,</l>
                  <l>Your thoughts beeing placed on him both day and night,</l>
                  <l>Your conſtant ſoule doth lodge betweene her breſts,</l>
                  <l>This Sweet of ſweets, in which all glory reſts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sometime h'appeares to thee in Shepheards weed,</l>
                  <l>And ſo preſents himſelfe before thine eyes,</l>
                  <l>A good old man; that goes his flocke to feed;</l>
                  <l>Thy colour changes, and thy heart doth riſe;</l>
                  <l>Thou call'ſt, he comes, thou find'ſt tis he indeed,</l>
                  <l>Thy Soule conceaues that he is truely wiſe:</l>
                  <l>Nay more, deſires that he may be the Booke,</l>
                  <l>Whereon thine eyes continually may looke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sometime impriſon'd, naked, poore, and bare,</l>
                  <l>Full of diſeaſes, impotent, and lame,</l>
                  <l>Blind, deafe, and dumbe, he comes vnto his faire,</l>
                  <l>To ſee if yet ſhee will remaine the ſame;</l>
                  <l>Nay ſicke and wounded, now thou do'ſt prepare</l>
                  <l>To cheriſh him in thy deare Louers name:</l>
                  <l>Yea thou beſtow'ſt all paines, all coſt, all care,</l>
                  <l>That may relieue him, and his health repaire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe workes of mercy are ſo ſweete, ſo deare</l>
                  <l>To him that is the Lord of Life and Loue,</l>
                  <l>That all thy prayers he vouchſafes to heare,</l>
                  <l>And ſends his holy Spirit from aboue;</l>
                  <l>Thy eyes are op'ned, and thou ſeeſt ſo cleare,</l>
                  <l>No worldly thing can thy faire mind remoue;</l>
                  <l>Thy faith, thy prayers, and his ſpeciall grace</l>
                  <l>Doth open Heau'n, where thou behold'ſt his face.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:45"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe are thoſe Keyes Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did poſſeſſe,</l>
                  <l>Which with a Spirituall powre are giu'n to thee,</l>
                  <l>To heale the ſoules of thoſe that doe tranſgreſſe,</l>
                  <l>By thy faire virtues; which, if once they ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the like they doe their minds addreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Such as thou art, ſuch they deſire to be:</l>
                  <l>If they be blind, thou giu'ſt to them their ſight;</l>
                  <l>If deafe or lame, they heare, and goe vpright.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yea, if poſſeſt with any euill ſpirits,</l>
                  <l>Such powre thy faire examples haue obtain'd</l>
                  <l>To caſt them out, applying Chriſts pure merits,</l>
                  <l>By which they are bound, and of all hurt reſtrain'd:</l>
                  <l>If ſtrangely taken, wanting ſence or wits,</l>
                  <l>Thy faith appli'd vnto their ſoules ſo pain'd,</l>
                  <l>Healeth all griefes, and makes them grow ſo ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>As no defects can hang vpon them long.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou beeing thus rich, no riches do'ſt reſpect,</l>
                  <l>Nor do'ſt thou care for any outward ſhowe;</l>
                  <l>The proud that doe faire Virtues rules neglect,</l>
                  <l>Deſiring place, thou fitteſt them belowe:</l>
                  <l>All wealth and honour thou do'ſt quite reiect,</l>
                  <l>If thou perceiu'ſt that once it prooues a foe</l>
                  <l>To virtue, learning, and the powres diuine,</l>
                  <l>Thou mai'ſt conuert, but neuer wilt incline</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To fowle diſorder, or licentiouſneſſe,</l>
                  <l>But in thy modeſt vaile do'ſt ſweetly couer</l>
                  <l>The ſtaines of other ſinnes, to make themſelues,</l>
                  <l>That by this meanes thou mai'ſt in time recouer</l>
                  <l>Thoſe weake loſt ſheepe that did ſo long tranſgreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Preſenting them vnto thy deereſt Louer;</l>
                  <l>That when he brings them backe vnto his fold,</l>
                  <l>In their conuerſion then he may behold</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:45"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy beauty ſhining brighter than the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>Thine honour more than euer Monarke gaind,</l>
                  <l>Thy wealth exceeding his that Kingdomes wonne,</l>
                  <l>Thy Loue vnto his Spouſe, thy Faith vnfaind,</l>
                  <l>Thy Conſtancy in what thou haſt begun,</l>
                  <l>Till thou his heauenly Kingdom haue obtaind;</l>
                  <l>Reſpecting worldly wealth to be but droſſe,</l>
                  <l>Which, if abuz'd, doth prooue the owners loſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great <hi>Cleopatra's</hi> loue to <hi>Anthony,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Can no way be compared vnto thine;</l>
                  <l>Shee left her Loue in his extremitie,</l>
                  <l>When greateſt need ſhould cauſe her to combine</l>
                  <l>Her force with his, to get the Victory:</l>
                  <l>Her Loue was earthly, and thy Loue Diuine;</l>
                  <l>Her Loue was onely to ſupport her pride,</l>
                  <l>Humilitie thy Loue and Thee doth guide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That glorious part of Death, which laſt ſhee plai'd,</l>
                  <l>T'appeaſe the ghoſt of her deceaſed Loue,</l>
                  <l>Had neuer needed, if ſhee could haue ſtai'd</l>
                  <l>When his extreames made triall, and did proue</l>
                  <l>Her leaden loue vnconſtant, and afraid:</l>
                  <l>Their wicked warres the wrath of God might moue</l>
                  <l>To take reuenge for chaſt <hi>Octavia's</hi> wrongs,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe ſhee enjoyes what vnto her belongs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> though thou wert as faire</l>
                  <l>As any Creature in <hi>Antonius</hi> eyes;</l>
                  <l>Yea though thou wert as rich, as wiſe, as rare,</l>
                  <l>As any Pen could write, or Wit deuiſe;</l>
                  <l>Yet with this Lady canſt thou not compare,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe inward virtues all thy worth denies:</l>
                  <l>Yet thou a blacke Egyptian do'ſt appeare;</l>
                  <l>Thou falſe, ſhee true; and to her Loue more deere.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:46"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shee ſacrificeth to her deereſt Loue,</l>
                  <l>With flowres of Faith, and garlands of Good deeds;</l>
                  <l>Shee flies not from him when afflictions proue,</l>
                  <l>Shee beares his croſſe, and ſtops his wounds that bleeds;</l>
                  <l>Shee loues and liues chaſte as the Turtle doue,</l>
                  <l>Shee attends vpon him, and his flocke ſhee feeds;</l>
                  <l>Yea for one touch of death which thou did'ſt trie,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand deaths ſhee euery day doth die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her virtuous life exceeds thy worthy death,</l>
                  <l>Yea, ſhe hath richer ornaments of ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Shining more glorious than in dying breath</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt; when either pride, or cruell fate,</l>
                  <l>Did worke thee to preuent a double death;</l>
                  <l>To ſtay the malice, ſcorne, and cruell hate</l>
                  <l>Of Rome; that joy'd to ſee thy pride pull'd downe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Beauty wrought the hazard of her Crowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good Madame, though your modeſtie be ſuch,</l>
                  <l>Not to acknowledge what we know and find;</l>
                  <l>And that you thinke theſe prayſes ouermuch,</l>
                  <l>Which doe expreſſe the beautie of your mind;</l>
                  <l>Yet pardon me although I giue a touch</l>
                  <l>Vnto their eyes, that elſe would be ſo blind,</l>
                  <l>As not to ſee thy ſtore, and their owne wants,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe faire ſeeds of Virtue ſpring theſe plants.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And knowe, when firſt into this world I came,</l>
                  <l>This charge was giu'n me by th'Eternall powres,</l>
                  <l>Th'euerlaſting Trophie of thy fame,</l>
                  <l>To build and decke it with the ſweeteſt flowres</l>
                  <l>That virtue yeelds; Then Madame, doe not blame</l>
                  <l>Me, when I ſhew the World but what is yours,</l>
                  <l>And decke you with that crowne which is your due,</l>
                  <l>That of Heau'ns beauty Earth may take a view.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:46"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though famous women elder times haue knowne,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe glorious actions did appeare ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>That powrefull men by them were ouerthrowne,</l>
                  <l>And all their armies ouercome in fight;</l>
                  <l>The Scythian women by their powre alone,</l>
                  <l>Put king <hi>Darius</hi> vnto ſhamefull flight:</l>
                  <l>All Aſia yeelded to their conq'ring hand,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Alexander</hi> could not their powre withſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe worth, though writ in lines of blood and fire,</l>
                  <l>Is not to be compared vnto thine;</l>
                  <l>Their powre was ſmall to ouercome Deſire,</l>
                  <l>Or to direct their wayes by Virtues line:</l>
                  <l>Were they aliue, they would thy Life admire,</l>
                  <l>And vnto thee their honours would reſigne:</l>
                  <l>For thou a greater conqueſt do'ſt obtaine,</l>
                  <l>Than they who haue ſo many thouſands ſlaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wiſe <hi>Deborah</hi> that judged Iſrael,</l>
                  <l>Nor valiant <hi>Iudeth</hi> cannot equall thee,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the firſt, God did his will reueale,</l>
                  <l>And gaue her powre to ſet his people free;</l>
                  <l>Yea <hi>Iudeth</hi> had the powre likewiſe to queale</l>
                  <l>Proud <hi>Holifernes,</hi> that the juſt might ſee</l>
                  <l>What ſmall defence vaine pride, and greatneſſe hath</l>
                  <l>Againſt the weapons of Gods word and faith.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But thou farre greater warre do'ſt ſtill maintaine,</l>
                  <l>Againſt that many headed monſter Sinne,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe mortall ſting hath many thouſand ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>And euery day freſh combates doe begin;</l>
                  <l>Yet cannot all his venome lay one ſtaine</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy Soule, thou do'ſt the conqueſt winne,</l>
                  <l>Though all the world he daily doth deuoure,</l>
                  <l>Yet ouer thee he neuer could get powre.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:47"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>For that one worthy deed by <hi>Deb'rah</hi> done,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt performed many in thy time;</l>
                  <l>For that one Conqueſt that faire <hi>Iudeth</hi> wonne,</l>
                  <l>By which ſhee did the ſteps of honour clime;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt the Conqueſt of all Conqueſts wonne,</l>
                  <l>When to thy Conſcience Hell can lay no crime:</l>
                  <l>For that one head that <hi>Iudeth</hi> bare away,</l>
                  <l>Thou tak'ſt from Sinne a hundred heads a day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though virtuous <hi>Hester</hi> faſted three dayes ſpace,</l>
                  <l>And ſpent her time in prayers all that while,</l>
                  <l>That by Gods powre ſhee might obtaine ſuch grace,</l>
                  <l>That ſhee and hers might not become a ſpoyle</l>
                  <l>To wicked <hi>Hamon,</hi> in whoſe crabbed face</l>
                  <l>Was ſeene the map of malice, enuie, guile;</l>
                  <l>Her glorious garments though ſhee put apart,</l>
                  <l>So to preſent a pure and ſingle heart</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To God, in ſack-cloth, aſhes, and with teares;</l>
                  <l>Yet muſt faire <hi>Heſter</hi> needs giue place to thee,</l>
                  <l>Who hath continu'd dayes, weekes, months, and yeares,</l>
                  <l>In Gods true ſeruice, yet thy heart beeing free</l>
                  <l>From doubt of death, or any other feares:</l>
                  <l>Faſting from ſinne, thou pray'ſt thine eyes may ſee</l>
                  <l>Him that hath full poſſeſſion of thine heart,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe ſweet loue thy Soule can neuer part.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His Loue, not Feare, makes thee to faſt and pray,</l>
                  <l>No kinſmans counſell needs thee to aduiſe;</l>
                  <l>The ſack-cloth thou do'ſt weare both night and day,</l>
                  <l>Is worldly troubles, which thy reſt denies;</l>
                  <l>The aſhes are the Vanities that play</l>
                  <l>Ouer thy head, and ſteale before thine eyes;</l>
                  <l>Which thou ſhak'ſt off when mourning time is paſt,</l>
                  <l>That royall roabes thou may'ſt put on at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:47"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioachims</hi> wife; that faire and conſtant Dame,</l>
                  <l>Who rather choſe a cruel death to die,</l>
                  <l>Than yeeld to thoſe two Elders voide of ſhame,</l>
                  <l>When both at once her chaſtitie did trie,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Innocencie bare away the blame,</l>
                  <l>Vntill th'Almighty Lord had heard her crie;</l>
                  <l>And rais'd the ſpirit of a Child to ſpeake,</l>
                  <l>Making the powrefull judged of the weake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Although her virtue doe deſerue to be</l>
                  <l>Writ by that hand that neuer purchas'd blame;</l>
                  <l>In holy Writ, where all the world may ſee</l>
                  <l>Her perfit life, and euer honoured name:</l>
                  <l>Yet was ſhe not to be compar'd to thee,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe many virtues doe increaſe thy fame:</l>
                  <l>For ſhee oppoſ'd againſt old doting Luſt,</l>
                  <l>Who with lifes danger ſhe did feare to truſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But your chafte breaſt, guarded with ſtrength of mind,</l>
                  <l>Hates the imbracements of vnchaſte deſires;</l>
                  <l>You louing God, liue in your ſelfe confind</l>
                  <l>From vnpure Loue, your pureſt thoughts retires,</l>
                  <l>Your perfit ſight could neuer be ſo blind,</l>
                  <l>To entertaine the old or yong deſires</l>
                  <l>Of idle Louers; which the world preſents,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe baſe abuſes worthy minds preuents.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Euen as the conſtant Lawrell, alwayes greene,</l>
                  <l>No parching heate of Summer can deface,</l>
                  <l>Nor pinching Winter euer yet was ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe nipping froſts could wither, or diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>So you (deere Ladie) ſtill remaine as Queene,</l>
                  <l>Subduing all affections that are baſe,</l>
                  <l>Vnalterable by the change of times,</l>
                  <l>Not following, but lamenting others crimes.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:48"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>No feare of Death, or dread of open ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Hinders your perfect heart to giue conſent;</l>
                  <l>Nor loathſome age, whom Time could neuer tame</l>
                  <l>From ill deſignes, whereto their youth was bent;</l>
                  <l>But loue of God, care to preſerue your fame,</l>
                  <l>And ſpend that pretious time that God hath ſent,</l>
                  <l>In all good exerciſes of the minde,</l>
                  <l>Whereto your noble nature is inclin'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That Ethyopian Queene did gaine great fame,</l>
                  <l>Who from the Southerne world, did come to ſee</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Salomon;</hi> the glory of whoſe name</l>
                  <l>Had ſpread it ſelfe ore all the earth, to be</l>
                  <l>So great, that all the Princes thither came,</l>
                  <l>To be ſpectators of his royaltie:</l>
                  <l>And this faire Queene of Sheba came from farre,</l>
                  <l>To reuerence this new appearing ſtarre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From th'vtmoſt part of all the Earth ſhee came,</l>
                  <l>To heare the Wiſdom of this worthy King;</l>
                  <l>To trie if Wonder did agree with Fame,</l>
                  <l>And many faire rich preſents did ſhe bring:</l>
                  <l>Yea many ſtrange hard queſtions did ſhee frame,</l>
                  <l>All which were anſwer'd by this famous King:</l>
                  <l>Nothing was hid that in her heart did reſt,</l>
                  <l>And all to prooue this King ſo highly bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here Maieſtie with Maieſtie did meete,</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome to Wiſdome yeelded true content,</l>
                  <l>One Beauty did another Beauty greet,</l>
                  <l>Bounty to Bountie neuer could repent;</l>
                  <l>Here all diſtaſte is troden vnder feet,</l>
                  <l>No loſſe of time, where time was ſo well ſpent</l>
                  <l>In virtuous exerciſes of the minde,</l>
                  <l>In which this Queene did much contentment finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:48"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Spirits affect where they doe ſympathize,</l>
                  <l>Wiſdom deſires Wiſdome to embrace,</l>
                  <l>Virtue couets her like, and doth deuize</l>
                  <l>How ſhe her friends may entertaine with grace;</l>
                  <l>Beauty ſometime is pleas'd to feed her eyes,</l>
                  <l>With viewing Beautie in anothers face:</l>
                  <l>Both good and bad in this point doe agree,</l>
                  <l>That each deſireth with his like to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And this Deſire did worke a ſtrange effect,</l>
                  <l>To drawe a Queene forth of her natiue Land,</l>
                  <l>Not yeelding to the niceneſſe and reſpect</l>
                  <l>Of woman-kind; ſhee paſt both ſea and land,</l>
                  <l>All feare of dangers ſhee did quite neglect,</l>
                  <l>Onely to ſee, to heare, and vnderſtand</l>
                  <l>That beauty, wiſedome, maieſtie, and glorie,</l>
                  <l>That in her heart impreſt his perfect ſtorie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet this faire map of maieſtie and might,</l>
                  <l>Was but a figure of thy deereſt Loue,</l>
                  <l>Borne t'expreſſe that true and heauenly light,</l>
                  <l>That doth all other joyes imperfect proue;</l>
                  <l>If this faire Earthly ſtarre did ſhine ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>What doth that glorious Sonne that is aboue?</l>
                  <l>Who weares th'imperiall crowne of heauen and earth,</l>
                  <l>And made all Chriſtians bleſſed in his berth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If that ſmall ſparke could yeeld ſo great a fire,</l>
                  <l>As to inflame the hearts of many Kings</l>
                  <l>To come to ſee, to heare, and to admire</l>
                  <l>His wiſdome, tending but to worldly things;</l>
                  <l>Then much more reaſon haue we to deſire</l>
                  <l>That heau'nly wiſedome, which ſaluation brings;</l>
                  <l>The Sonne of righteouſneſſe, that giues true joyes,</l>
                  <l>When all they ſought for, were but Earthly toyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:49"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>No trauels ought th'affected ſoule to ſhunne,</l>
                  <l>That this faire heauenly Light deſires to ſee:</l>
                  <l>This King of kings to whom we all ſhould runne,</l>
                  <l>To view his Glory and his Majeſtie;</l>
                  <l>He without whom we all had beene vndone,</l>
                  <l>He that from Sinne and Death hath ſet vs free,</l>
                  <l>And ouercome Satan, the world, and finne,</l>
                  <l>That by his merits we thoſe joyes might winne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Prepar'd by him, whoſe euerlaſting throne</l>
                  <l>Is plac'd in heauen, aboue the ſtarrie skies,</l>
                  <l>Where he that ſate, was like the Iaſper ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Who rightly knowes him ſhall be truely wiſe,</l>
                  <l>A Rainebow round about his glorious throne;</l>
                  <l>Nay more, thoſe winged beaſts ſo full of eies,</l>
                  <l>That neuer ceaſe to glorifie his Name,</l>
                  <l>Who was, and will be, and is now the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is that great almightie Lord that made</l>
                  <l>Both heauen and earth, and liues for euermore;</l>
                  <l>By him the worlds foundation firſt was laid:</l>
                  <l>He fram'd the things that neuer were before:</l>
                  <l>The Sea within his bounds by him is ſtaid,</l>
                  <l>He judgeth all alike, both rich and poore:</l>
                  <l>All might, all majeſtie, all loue, all lawe</l>
                  <l>Remaines in him that keepes all worlds in awe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From his eternall throne the lightning came,</l>
                  <l>Thundrings and Voyces did from thence proceede;</l>
                  <l>And all the creatures glorifi'd his name,</l>
                  <l>In heauen, in earth, and ſeas, they all agreed,</l>
                  <l>When loe that ſpotleſſe Lambe ſo voyd of blame,</l>
                  <l>That for vs di'd, whoſe ſinnes did make him bleed:</l>
                  <l>That true Phyſition that ſo many heales,</l>
                  <l>Opened the Booke, and did vndoe the Seales.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:49"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>He onely worthy to vndoe the Booke</l>
                  <l>Of our charg'd ſoules, full of iniquitie,</l>
                  <l>Where with the eyes of mercy he doth looke</l>
                  <l>Vpon our weakeneſſe and infirmitie;</l>
                  <l>This is that corner ſtone that was forſooke,</l>
                  <l>Who leaues it, truſts but to vncertaintie:</l>
                  <l>This is Gods Sonne, in whom he is well pleaſed,</l>
                  <l>His deere beloued, that his wrath appeaſed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that had powre to open all the Seales,</l>
                  <l>And ſummon vp our ſinnes of blood and wrong,</l>
                  <l>He vnto whom the righteous ſoules appeales,</l>
                  <l>That haue bin martyrd, and doe thinke it long,</l>
                  <l>To whom in mercie he his will reueales,</l>
                  <l>That they ſhould reſt a little in their wrong,</l>
                  <l>Vntill their fellow ſeruants ſhould be killed,</l>
                  <l>Euen as they were, and that they were fulfilled.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dowager of Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Pure thoughted Lady, bleſſed be thy choyce</l>
                  <l>Of this Almightie, euerlaſting King;</l>
                  <l>In thee his Saints and Angels doe reioyce,</l>
                  <l>And to their Heau'nly Lord doe daily ſing</l>
                  <l>Thy perfect praiſes in their lowdeſt voyce;</l>
                  <l>And all their harpes and golden vials bring</l>
                  <l>Full of ſweet odours, euen thy-holy prayers</l>
                  <l>Vnto that ſpotleſſe Lambe, that all repaires.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of whom that Heathen Queene obtain'd ſuch grace,</l>
                  <l>By honouring but the ſhadow of his Loue,</l>
                  <l>That great Iudiciall day to haue a place,</l>
                  <l>Condemning thoſe that doe vnfaithfull proue;</l>
                  <l>Among the hapleſſe, happie is her caſe,</l>
                  <l>That her deere Sauiour ſpake for her behoue;</l>
                  <l>And that her memorable Act ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Writ by the hand of true Eternitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:50"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet this rare Phoenix of that worne-out age,</l>
                  <l>This great maieſticke Queene comes ſhort of thee,</l>
                  <l>Who to an earthly Prince did then ingage</l>
                  <l>Her hearts deſires, her loue, her libertie,</l>
                  <l>Acting her glorious part vpon a Stage</l>
                  <l>Of weakneſſe, frailtie, and infirmity:</l>
                  <l>Giuing all honour to a Creature, due</l>
                  <l>To her Creator, whom ſhee neuer knew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But loe, a greater thou haſt ſought and found</l>
                  <l>Than <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his royaltie;</l>
                  <l>And vnto him thy faith moſt firmely bound</l>
                  <l>To ſerue and honour him continually;</l>
                  <l>That glorious God, whoſe terror doth confound</l>
                  <l>All ſinfull workers of iniquitie:</l>
                  <l>Him haſt thou truely ſerued all thy life,</l>
                  <l>And for his loue, liu'd with the world at ſtrife.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To this great Lord, thou onely art affected,</l>
                  <l>Yet came he not in pompe or royaltie,</l>
                  <l>But in an humble habit, baſe, deiected;</l>
                  <l>A King, a God, clad in mortalitie,</l>
                  <l>He hath thy loue, thou art by him directed,</l>
                  <l>His perfect path was faire humilitie:</l>
                  <l>Who being Monarke of heau'n, earth, and ſeas,</l>
                  <l>Indur'd all wrongs, yet no man did diſpleaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then how much more art thou to be commended,</l>
                  <l>That ſeek'ſt thy loue in lowly ſhepheards weed?</l>
                  <l>A ſeeming Trades-mans ſonne, of none attended,</l>
                  <l>Saue of a few in pouertie and need;</l>
                  <l>Poore Fiſhermen that on his loue attended,</l>
                  <l>His loue that makes ſo many thouſands bleed:</l>
                  <l>Thus did he come, to trie our faiths the more,</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſſing worlds, yet ſeeming extreame poore.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:50"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Pilgrimes trauels, and the Shepheards cares,</l>
                  <l>He tooke vpon him to enlarge our ſoules,</l>
                  <l>What pride hath loſt, humilitie repaires,</l>
                  <l>For by his glorious death he vs inroules</l>
                  <l>In deepe Characters, writ with blood and teares,</l>
                  <l>Vpon thoſe bleſſed Euerlaſting ſcroules;</l>
                  <l>His hands, his feete, his body, and his face,</l>
                  <l>Whence freely flow'd the riuers of his grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sweet holy riuers, pure celeſtiall ſprings,</l>
                  <l>Proceeding from the fountaine of our life;</l>
                  <l>Swift ſugred currents that ſaluation brings,</l>
                  <l>Cleare chriſtall ſtreames, purging all ſinne and ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Faire floods, where ſouls do bathe their ſnow-white wings,</l>
                  <l>Before they flie to true etern all life:</l>
                  <l>Sweet Nectar and Ambroſia, food of Saints,</l>
                  <l>Which, whoſo taſteth, neuer after faints.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This hony dropping dew of holy loue,</l>
                  <l>Sweet milke, wherewith we weaklings are reſtored,</l>
                  <l>Who drinkes thereof, a world can neuer moue,</l>
                  <l>All earthly pleaſures are of them abhorred;</l>
                  <l>This loue made Martyrs many deaths to proue,</l>
                  <l>To taſte his ſweetneſſe, whom they ſo adored:</l>
                  <l>Sweetneſſe that makes our fleſh a burthen to vs,</l>
                  <l>Knowing it ſerues but onely to vndoe vs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His ſweetneſſe ſweet'ned all the ſowre of death,</l>
                  <l>To faithfull <hi>Stephen</hi> his appointed Saint;</l>
                  <l>Who by the riuer ſtones did looſe his breath,</l>
                  <l>When paines nor terrors could not make him faint:</l>
                  <l>So was this bleſſed Martyr turn'd to earth,</l>
                  <l>To glorifie his ſoule by deaths attaint:</l>
                  <l>This holy Saint was humbled and caſt downe,</l>
                  <l>To winne in heauen an euerlaſting crowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:51"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe face repleat with Maieſtie and Sweetneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Did as an Angel vnto them appeare,</l>
                  <l>That ſate in Counſell hearing his diſcreetneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Seeing no change, or any ſigne of a feare;</l>
                  <l>But with a conſtant browe did there confeſſe</l>
                  <l>Chriſts high deſerts, which were to him ſo deare:</l>
                  <l>Yea when theſe Tyrants ſtormes did moſt oppreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt did appeare to make his griefe the leſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For beeing filled with the holy Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>Vp vnto Heau'n he look'd with ſtedfaſt eies,</l>
                  <l>Where God appeared with his heauenly hoſte</l>
                  <l>In glory to this Saint before he dies;</l>
                  <l>Although he could no Earthly pleaſures boaſt,</l>
                  <l>At Gods right hand ſweet IESVS he eſpies;</l>
                  <l>Bids them behold Heauens open, he doth ſee</l>
                  <l>The Sonne of Man at Gods right hand to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe ſweetneſſe ſweet'ned that ſhort ſowre of Life,</l>
                  <l>Making all bitterneſſe delight his taſte,</l>
                  <l>Yeelding ſweet quietneſſe in bitter ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>And moſt contentment when he di'd diſgrac'd;</l>
                  <l>Heaping vp joyes where ſorrows were moſt rife;</l>
                  <l>Such ſweetneſſe could not chooſe but be imbrac'd:</l>
                  <l>The food of Soules, the Spirits onely treaſure,</l>
                  <l>The Paradiſe of our celeſtiall pleaſure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Lambe of God, who di'd, and was aliue,</l>
                  <l>Preſenting vs the bread of life Eternall,</l>
                  <l>His bruiſed body powrefull to reuiue</l>
                  <l>Our ſinking ſoules, out of the pit infernall;</l>
                  <l>For by this bleſſed food he did contriue</l>
                  <l>A worke of grace, by this his gift externall,</l>
                  <l>With heau'nly Manna, food of his elected,</l>
                  <l>To feed their ſoules, of whom he is reſpected.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:51"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>This wheate of Heauen the bleſſed Angells bread,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith he feedes his deere adopted Heires;</l>
                  <l>Sweet foode of life that doth reuiue the dead,</l>
                  <l>And from the liuing takes away all cares;</l>
                  <l>To taſte this ſweet Saint <hi>Laurence</hi> did not dread,</l>
                  <l>The broyling gridyorne cool'd with holy teares:</l>
                  <l>Yeelding his naked body to the fire,</l>
                  <l>To taſte this ſweetneſſe, ſuch was his deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, what great ſweetneſſe did th'Apoſtles taſte,</l>
                  <l>Condemn'd by Counſell, when they did returne;</l>
                  <l>Rejoycing that for him they di'd diſgrac'd,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſweetnes made their hearts and ſoules ſo burne</l>
                  <l>With holy zeale and loue moſt pure and chaſte;</l>
                  <l>For him they ſought from whome they might not turne:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe loue made <hi>Andrew</hi> goe moſt joyfully,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Croſſe, on which he meant to die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Princes of th'Apoſtles were ſo filled</l>
                  <l>With the delicious ſweetnes of his grace,</l>
                  <l>That willingly they yeelded to be killed,</l>
                  <l>Receiuing deaths that were moſt vile and baſe,</l>
                  <l>For his name ſake, that all might be fulfilled.</l>
                  <l>They with great joy all torments did imbrace:</l>
                  <l>The vgli'ſt face that Death could euer yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Could neuer feare theſe Champions from the field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They ſtill continued in their glorious fight,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the enemies of fleſh and blood;</l>
                  <l>And in Gods law did ſet their whole delight,</l>
                  <l>Suppreſſing euill, and erecting good:</l>
                  <l>Not ſparing Kings in what they did not right;</l>
                  <l>Their noble Actes they ſeal'd with deereſt blood:</l>
                  <l>One choſe the Gallowes, that vnſeemely death,</l>
                  <l>The other by the Sword did looſe his breath.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:52"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>His Head did pay the deareſt rate of ſin,</l>
                  <l>Yeelding it joyfully vnto the Sword,</l>
                  <l>To be cut off as he had neuer bin,</l>
                  <l>For ſpeaking truth according to Gods word,</l>
                  <l>Telling king <hi>Herod</hi> of inceſtuous ſin,</l>
                  <l>That hatefull crime of God and man abhorr'd:</l>
                  <l>His brothers wife, that prowd licentious Dame,</l>
                  <l>Cut off his Head to take away his ſhame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe Madame, heere you take a view of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worthy ſteps you doe deſire to tread,</l>
                  <l>Deckt in thoſe colours which our Sauiour choſe;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Colours of Confeſſors &amp; Martirs.</note> The pureſt colours both of White and Red,</l>
                  <l>Their freſheſt beauties would I faine diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>By which our Sauiour moſt was honoured:</l>
                  <l>But my weake Muſe deſireth now to reſt,</l>
                  <l>Folding vp all their Beauties in your breaſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe excellence hath rais'd my ſprites to write,</l>
                  <l>Of what my thoughts could hardly apprehend;</l>
                  <l>Your rareſt Virtues did my ſoule delight,</l>
                  <l>Great Ladie of my heart: I muſt commend</l>
                  <l>You that appeare ſo faire in all mens fight:</l>
                  <l>On your Deſerts my Muſes doe attend:</l>
                  <l>You are the Articke Starre that guides my hand,</l>
                  <l>All what I am, I reſt at your command.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:52"/>
            <head>The Deſcription of Cooke-ham</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FArewell (ſweet <hi>Cooke-ham</hi>) where I firſt obtain'd</l>
               <l>Grace from that Grace where perfit Grace remain'd;</l>
               <l>And where the Muſes gaue their full conſent,</l>
               <l>I ſhould haue powre the virtuous to content:</l>
               <l>Where princely Palace will'd me to indite,</l>
               <l>The ſacred Storie of the Soules delight.</l>
               <l>Farewell (ſweet Place) where Virtue then did reſt,</l>
               <l>And all delights did harbour in her breaſt:</l>
               <l>Neuer ſhall my ſad eies againe behold</l>
               <l>Thoſe pleaſures which my thoughts did then vnfold:</l>
               <l>Yet you (great Lady) Miſtris of that Place,</l>
               <l>From whoſe deſires did ſpring this worke of Grace;</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe to thinke vpon thoſe pleaſures paſt,</l>
               <l>As fleeting worldly Ioyes that could not laſt:</l>
               <l>Or, as dimme ſhadowes of celeſtiall pleaſures,</l>
               <l>Which are deſir'd aboue all earthly treaſures.</l>
               <l>Oh how (me thought) againſt you thither came,</l>
               <l>Each part did ſeeme ſome new delight to frame!</l>
               <l>The Houſe receiu'd all ornaments to grace it,</l>
               <l>And would indure no fouleneſſe to deface it.</l>
               <l>The Walkes put on their ſummer Liueries,</l>
               <l>And all things elſe did hold like ſimilies:</l>
               <l>The Trees with leaues, with fruits, with flowers clad,</l>
               <l>Embrac'd each other, ſeeming to be glad,</l>
               <l>Turning themſelues to beauteous Canopies,</l>
               <l>To ſhade the bright Sunne from your brighter eies:</l>
               <l>The criſtall Streames with ſiluer ſpangles graced,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:53"/>
               <l>While by the glorious Sunne they were embraced:</l>
               <l>The little Birds in chirping notes did ſing,</l>
               <l>To entertaine both You and that ſweet Spring.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Philomela</hi> with her ſundry layes,</l>
               <l>Both You and that delightfull Place did praiſe.</l>
               <l>Oh how me thought each plant, each floure, each tree</l>
               <l>Set forth their beauties then to welcome thee!</l>
               <l>The very Hills right humbly did deſcend,</l>
               <l>When you to tread vpon them did intend.</l>
               <l>And as you ſet your feete, they ſtill did riſe,</l>
               <l>Glad that they could receiue ſo rich a priſe.</l>
               <l>The gentle Windes did take delight to bee</l>
               <l>Among thoſe woods that were ſo grac'd by thee.</l>
               <l>And in ſad murmure vtterd pleaſing ſound,</l>
               <l>That Pleaſure in that place might more abound:</l>
               <l>The ſwelling Bankes deliuer'd all their pride,</l>
               <l>When ſuch a <hi>Phoenix</hi> once they had eſpide.</l>
               <l>Each Arbor, Banke, each Seate, each ſtately Tree,</l>
               <l>Thought themſelues honor'd in ſupporting thee.</l>
               <l>The pretty Birds would oft come to attend thee,</l>
               <l>Yet flie away for feare they ſhould offend thee:</l>
               <l>The little creatures in the Burrough by</l>
               <l>Would come abroad to ſport them in your eye;</l>
               <l>Yet fearefull of the Bowe in your faire Hand,</l>
               <l>Would runne away when you did make a ſtand.</l>
               <l>Now let me come vnto that ſtately Tree,</l>
               <l>Wherein ſuch goodly Proſpects you did ſee;</l>
               <l>That Oake that did in height his fellowes paſſe,</l>
               <l>As much as lofty trees, low growing graſſe:</l>
               <l>Much like a comely Cedar ſtreight and tall,</l>
               <l>Whoſe beauteous ſtature farre exceeded all:</l>
               <l>How often did you viſite this faire tree,</l>
               <l>Which ſeeming joyfull in receiuing thee,</l>
               <l>Would like a Palme tree ſpread his armes abroad,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:53"/>
               <l>Deſirous that you there ſhould make abode:</l>
               <l>Whoſe faire greene leaues much like a comely vaile,</l>
               <l>Defended <hi>Phebus</hi> when he would aſſaile:</l>
               <l>Whoſe pleaſing boughes did yeeld a coole freſh ayre,</l>
               <l>Ioying his happineſſe when you were there.</l>
               <l>Where beeing ſeated, you might plainely ſee,</l>
               <l>Hills, vales, and woods, as if on bended knee</l>
               <l>They had appeard, your honour to ſalute,</l>
               <l>Or to preferre ſome ſtrange vnlook'd for ſute:</l>
               <l>All interlac'd with brookes and chriſtall ſprings,</l>
               <l>A Proſpect fit to pleaſe the eyes of Kings:</l>
               <l>And thirteene ſhires appear'd all in your ſight,</l>
               <l>Europe could not affoard much more delight.</l>
               <l>What was there then but gaue you all content,</l>
               <l>While you the time in meditation ſpent,</l>
               <l>Of their Creators powre, which there you ſaw,</l>
               <l>In all his Creatures held a perfit Law;</l>
               <l>And in their beauties did you plaine deſcrie,</l>
               <l>His beauty, wiſdome, grace, loue, maieſtie.</l>
               <l>In theſe ſweet woods how often did you walke,</l>
               <l>With Chriſt and his Apoſtles there to talke;</l>
               <l>Placing his holy Writ in ſome faire tree,</l>
               <l>To meditate what you therein did ſee:</l>
               <l>With <hi>Moyſes</hi> you did mount his holy Hill,</l>
               <l>To know his pleaſure, and performe his Will,</l>
               <l>With louely <hi>Dauid</hi> you did often ſing,</l>
               <l>His holy Hymnes to Heauens Eternall King.</l>
               <l>And in ſweet muſicke did your ſoule delight,</l>
               <l>To ſound his prayſes, morning, noone, and night.</l>
               <l>With bleſſed <hi>Ioſeph</hi> you did often feed</l>
               <l>Your pined brethren, when they ſtood in need.</l>
               <l>And that ſweet Lady ſprung from <hi>Cliffords</hi> race,</l>
               <l>Of noble <hi>Bedfords</hi> blood, faire ſteame of Grace;</l>
               <l>To honourable <hi>Dorſet</hi> now eſpowſ'd,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:54"/>
               <l>In whoſe faire breaſt true virtue then was houſ'd:</l>
               <l>Oh what delight did my weake ſpirits find</l>
               <l>In thoſe pure parts of her well framed mind:</l>
               <l>And yet it grieues me that I cannot be</l>
               <l>Neere vnto her, whoſe virtues did agree</l>
               <l>With thoſe faire ornaments of outward beauty,</l>
               <l>Which did enforce from all both loue and dutie.</l>
               <l>Vnconſtant Fortune, thou art moſt too blame,</l>
               <l>Who caſts vs downe into ſo lowe a frame:</l>
               <l>Where our great friends we cannot dayly ſee,</l>
               <l>So great a diffrence is there in degree.</l>
               <l>Many are placed in thoſe Orbes of ſtate,</l>
               <l>Parters in honour, ſo ordain'd by Fate;</l>
               <l>Neerer in ſhow, yet farther off in loue,</l>
               <l>In which, the loweſt alwayes are aboue.</l>
               <l>But whither am I carried in conceit?</l>
               <l>My Wit too weake to conſter of the great.</l>
               <l>Why not? although we are but borne of earth,</l>
               <l>We may behold the Heauens, deſpiſing death;</l>
               <l>And louing heauen that is ſo farre aboue,</l>
               <l>May in the end vouchſafe vs entire loue.</l>
               <l>Therefore ſweet Memorie doe thou retaine</l>
               <l>Thoſe pleaſures paſt, which will not turne againe:</l>
               <l>Remember beauteous <hi>Dorſets</hi> former ſports,</l>
               <l>So farre from beeing toucht by ill reports;</l>
               <l>Wherein my ſelfe did alwaies beare a part,</l>
               <l>While reuerend Loue preſented my true heart:</l>
               <l>Thoſe recreations let me beare in mind,</l>
               <l>Which her ſweet youth and noble thoughts did finde:</l>
               <l>Whereof depriu'd, I euermore muſt grieue,</l>
               <l>Hating blind Fortune, careleſſe to relieue.</l>
               <l>And you ſweet Cooke-ham, whom theſe Ladies leaue,</l>
               <l>I now muſt tell the griefe you did conceaue</l>
               <l>At their departure; when they went away,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:54"/>
               <l>How euery thing retaind a ſad diſmay:</l>
               <l>Nay long before, when once an inkeling came,</l>
               <l>Me thought each thing did vnto ſorrow frame:</l>
               <l>The trees that were ſo glorious in our view,</l>
               <l>Forſooke both flowres and fruit, when once they knew</l>
               <l>Of your depart, their very leaues did wither,</l>
               <l>Changing their colours as they grewe together.</l>
               <l>But when they ſaw this had no powre to ſtay you,</l>
               <l>They often wept, though ſpeechleſſe, could not pray you;</l>
               <l>Letting their teares in your faire boſoms fall,</l>
               <l>As if they ſaid, Why will ye leaue vs all?</l>
               <l>This being vaine, they caſt their leaues away,</l>
               <l>Hoping that pitie would haue made you ſtay:</l>
               <l>Their frozen tops, like Ages hoarie haires,</l>
               <l>Showes their diſaſters, languiſhing in feares:</l>
               <l>A ſwarthy riueld ryne all ouer ſpread,</l>
               <l>Their dying bodies halfe aliue, halfe dead.</l>
               <l>But your occaſions call'd you ſo away,</l>
               <l>That nothing there had power to make you ſtay:</l>
               <l>Yet did I ſee a noble gratefull minde,</l>
               <l>Requiting each according to their kind;</l>
               <l>Forgetting not to turne and take your leaue</l>
               <l>Of theſe ſad creatures, powreleſſe to receiue</l>
               <l>Your fauour, when with griefe you did depart,</l>
               <l>Placing their former pleaſures in your heart;</l>
               <l>Giuing great charge to noble Memory,</l>
               <l>There to preſerue their loue continually:</l>
               <l>But ſpecially the loue of that faire tree,</l>
               <l>That firſt and laſt you did vouchſafe to ſee:</l>
               <l>In which it pleas'd you oft to take the ayre,</l>
               <l>With noble <hi>Dorſet,</hi> then a virgin faire:</l>
               <l>Where many a learned Booke was read and skand</l>
               <l>To this faire tree, taking me by the hand,</l>
               <l>You did repeat the pleaſures which had paſt,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:55"/>
               <l>Seeming to grieue they could no longer laſt.</l>
               <l>And with a chaſte, yet louing kiſſe tooke leaue,</l>
               <l>Of which ſweet kiſſe I did it ſoone bereaue:</l>
               <l>Scorning a ſenceleſſe creature ſhould poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>So rare a fauour, ſo great happineſſe.</l>
               <l>No other kiſſe it could receiue from me,</l>
               <l>For feare to giue backe what it tooke of thee:</l>
               <l>So I ingratefull Creature did deceiue it,</l>
               <l>Of that which you vouchſaft in loue to leaue it.</l>
               <l>And though it oft had giu'n me much content,</l>
               <l>Yet this great wrong I neuer could repent:</l>
               <l>But of the happieſt made it moſt forlorne,</l>
               <l>To ſhew that nothing's free from Fortunes ſcorne,</l>
               <l>While all the reſt with this moſt beauteous tree,</l>
               <l>Made their ſad conſort Sorrowes harmony.</l>
               <l>The Floures that on the banks and walkes did grow,</l>
               <l>Crept in the ground, the Graſſe did weepe for woe.</l>
               <l>The Windes and Waters ſeem'd to chide together,</l>
               <l>Becauſe you went away they knew not whither:</l>
               <l>And thoſe ſweet Brookes that ranne ſo faire and cleare,</l>
               <l>With griefe and trouble wrinckled did appeare.</l>
               <l>Thoſe pretty Birds that wonted were to ſing,</l>
               <l>Now neither ſing, nor chirp, nor vſe their wing;</l>
               <l>But with their tender feet on ſome bare ſpray,</l>
               <l>Warble forth ſorrow, and their owne diſmay.</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Philomela</hi> leaues her mournefull Ditty,</l>
               <l>Drownd in dead ſleepe, yet can procure no pittie:</l>
               <l>Each arbour, banke, each ſeate, each ſtately tree,</l>
               <l>Lookes bare and deſolate now for want of thee;</l>
               <l>Turning greene treſſes into froſtie gray,</l>
               <l>While in cold griefe they wither all away.</l>
               <l>The Sunne grew weake, his beames no comfort gaue,</l>
               <l>While all greene things did make the earth their graue:</l>
               <l>Each brier, each bramble, when you went away,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:29214:55"/>
               <l>Caught faſt your clothes, thinking to make you ſtay:</l>
               <l>Delightfull Eccho wonted to reply</l>
               <l>To our laſt words, did now for ſorrow die:</l>
               <l>The houſe caſt off each garment that might grace it,</l>
               <l>Putting on Duſt and Cobwebs to deface it.</l>
               <l>All deſolation then there did appeare,</l>
               <l>When you were going whom they held ſo deare.</l>
               <l>This laſt farewell to <hi>Cooke-ham</hi> here I giue,</l>
               <l>When I am dead thy name in this may liue,</l>
               <l>Wherein I haue perform'd her noble heſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe virtues lodge in my vnworthy breaſt,</l>
               <l>And euer ſhall, ſo long as life remaines,</l>
               <l>Tying my heart to her by thoſe rich chaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_doubtful_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:56"/>
            <head>¶ To the doubtfull Reader.</head>
            <p>GEntle Reader, if thou deſire to be reſolued, why I giue this Title, <hi>Salue Deus Rex Iudaeorum,</hi> know for certaine, that it was deliuered vnto me in ſleepe many yeares before I had any intent to write in this maner, and was quite out of my memory, vntill I had written the Paſſion of Christ, when immediately it came into my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, what I had dreamed long before; and thinking it a ſignificant token, that I was appointed to performe this Worke, I gaue the very ſame words I receiued in ſleepe as the fittest Title I could deuiſe for this Booke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29214:56"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
